This is Estonia!
Estonia, what's going on? Can you answer?
Mayday! Mayday!
Are you coming to the rescue?
It looks really bad here now.
Really bad.
Estonia is not
any accident.
It is an extremely pervasive
and serious accident
-with very many victims,
and many, many concerned.
The ferry accident is
the greatest human tragedy
-which has affected the Nordic region
after the Second World War.
852 people lost their lives.
760 remain in the depths of the sea.
Estonia capsized and sank
in just a few minutes.
How could this happen?
The idea that we should
forget the Estonia accident
-without being sure of what
what happened is completely absurd.
My son is somewhere in the Baltic Sea.
But no one tells why
he is lying there.
And I still do not understand today
why the ship sank.
What really happened to Estonia?
The cause of the accident seems to be
-that the bow visor does not
was properly closed.
There was
several explosive charges on board.
The Accident Investigation Board
have wanted to obscure ...
... that the official statement
not true.
This is not anymore
just an accident and a tragedy.
There's something more behind this.
The investigation appears
as a great betrayal.
A rule of law goes to the bottom
with investigating what is the cause.
Are there then views on
that this should be supplemented by
-and go down and look,
then you respect that.
I think more young journalists
should go out again
-and take the opportunity to dive
as long as the wreck remains there.
Oh!
It seems like the Coast Guard
waiting for us.
Nothing should stop young journalists
to investigate the case themselves.
-What is your purpose?
-We are documentary filmmakers.
We're making a documentary
about the Estonia accident.
The Finnish Maritime Administration announces
that they believe that the
-over Estonia has been broken,
despite urges not to do so.
You can not let a ferry
with 850 people just lying
-when the truth does not come out.
I must not rest in my soul
until I get a definitive answer.
Sooner or later
the truth always comes out.
Wait. What the hell!
Oh, fucking! Oh, fucking!
It was very beautiful weather
in Tallinn during the day.
Autumn might have arrived
a little further than in Stockholm.
By September, I had just turned 20.
Then I went to Estonia to
greetings to my father, who worked there.
I decided to go home
just the day before, I think-
-because I was going home and working
on one of all my extra jobs.
My colleague had received
two free tickets and asked me
-if I wanted to hang on
and see what it looked like over there
-after they had become free
from the Soviet Union and so on.
1994 so I guess I am
a Christian, adventurous girl.
I'm going to Bible school.
Going to Estonia was something
which the Bible school had as a tradition.
It was exciting, because it was
my first real trip abroad.
I had just become a father. My
daughter Wilma was not many months old.
This was actually the first time
as I was some time away from home.
I was in Estonia because of
that I was going on a conference trip.
I was very much on the boat
while the boat was in port.
I remember
when I arrived at the port.
I was so fascinated
how big the ship was.
It's quite large.
It is 150 meters long, just over.
For the Estonians, that is it
something big and new to come.
We all ester were very proud
that we had such a modern
-and beautiful ferry, and so on.
Maybe it was also a symbol of
how in just a few years-
-had come forward in time
and could show such a ferry
-for those who went to Estonia
for the first time perhaps in his life.
My dad drove me to the boat
in the afternoon.
When we stood in the parking lot
so we called mom.
He had one like that
huge cell phone, you know.
She was worried about
that I would cross the Baltic Sea
-when it blew so much.
Storm warning:Gulf of Finland,
northern Baltic Sea, Åland Sea
-The archipelago sea. Tomorrow, western
or northwesterly storm, 21 m / s.
I drove the truck on the ferry-
-and drove in through the bow,
where the bow visor is open.
When I get out of the car, they say
just for me to apply the handbrake.
Then I do not see
that they do something more with the cars.
There are no cars strapped in,
even though it's windy.
The trip to Estonia
was planned well in advance.
Then Hjørund's mother called me
and asked if he could come along.
Hjørund said that he was very happy
wanted to follow
-and I could not think of
any reason to say no.
But in retrospect, I have thought:
"What if I said no?"
We have our cabins at the very bottom.
Really farthest under car tires.
It was cramped little cabins.
Four beds.
No windows - nothing more.
And that's where you travel
when traveling cheap.
I remember walking around and
thought:"How hard it is to find!"
It was not completely obvious
where to go.
The floor plan was confusing,
with many narrow corridors.
I decided to
to spend the night in the dining room
-instead of the claustrophobic
the cab under the car deck.
As fast as the boat
left the port of Tallinn
- so you got out pretty quickly
on the high seas
-and it started rocking quite early.
I walk around on the boat
and meetings with co-workers.
Then we decide to go
to the so-called karaoke bar.
Because there were vacant bar stools.
But the ship heeled so much-
-so could not sit
on the bar stools.
It's probably also called Admirals Pub.
Inside the Pub Admiral
so it's karaoke night.
We had heard that the first couple out
in the karaoke machine-
-are invited for a drink.
Then my friends thought:
"Well, then we take it! We take first
the number, and we'll take the free drink. "
Non-alcoholic, of course.
I decide to sing
this gospel song "Oh happy day".
-Oh happy day ...
-Oh happy day!
There were a lot of people in the pub, I know.
We thought it was very fun.
And so we get that drink,
of course. That was the goal.
Then I know
that I said hello then to them-
-and then I went down to my cabin.
That was the last time
I saw those classmates.
At ten o'clock, roughly, decide
we us to go to bed.
My colleague has arranged his own cabin.
The reason for that is
that he snores so much-
-so he thinks
that I would be allowed to sleep alone.
We say good night. My colleague
goes to his cabin on the starboard side
-and I go to my cabin
on the port side.
I know the clock
should have been around twelve at night.
I hear someone's digital clock like
says "beep-beep". It's twelve o'clock.
A little after twelve, then it slams.
Two very powerful bangs.
It sounds
as if the ship was going through ice.
That which makes us jerk
and wake up are-
-that it suddenly
comes a slant.
That's where my bunk starts to lean.
It tilts like this at once. It is
slope, and the slope remains.
I'm not that person at all
who usually rush out undressed-
-but the ur-instinct makes me
immediately rush out in just boxer shorts.
And when I get around the corner
then I see that there will be water-
-which rushes in along the wall.
I do not know where the water comes from
from, but this is speeding me up.
The battle side is all the time
jerkily worse. It continues.
All the glasses that were on the tables
drove around and was crushed.
Then I tell my co-workers
that we should leave the ship - out.
While I rush up the stairs
so I want to remember that I hear-
-an alarm signal without pauses. "Rrrrr."
Bottles are smashed in the duty-free shop,
which is on the fifth deck.
And all of a sudden, in front of my eyes
on me, unloads a drink vending machine
-and goes down and thumps in the wall.
A guy shouts, "Take it easy!"
I remember saying something:
"Shit in him!
This is not damn calm. "
Silja Europa. Viking. Estonia.
Estonia, Estonia.
Mayday, mayday.
Estonia, Silja Europa.
Ropar ni mayday?
Estonia, what's going on? Can you answer?
Yes, we have problems here.
We have a strong tilt towards starboard,
probably more than 20 or 30 degrees.
Can you come to the rescue?
and try to get Mariella with you?
Yes, Mariella is behind us
and have probably heard you.
Can you give us your position?
We have blackout and we ...
I do not really know now ...
Okay, we'm getting started
with the necessary measures.
It's tough to get to the exit.
I experience it as
-that she leans so much that we
almost will not stuff this.
I remember many around me
stood frozen. They did nothing.
I remember one person
standing on a sofa.
She just stands and screams straight out.
I look at her screaming
-but I hear nothing.
We're on the deck where you go on board,
so we are in a large, open hall.
Where the hall ends is the exit
to tires. And that's where everyone wants to be.
We are many people standing there.
Everyone is holding the stair railing.
If you drop the grip, you fall
down into the abyss and die.
When we stand there, it's a girl
who loses his grip in front of me.
She's going at a high speed,
hits in the head and goes further down.
Then I just think:
"I do not want to see this."
And then I see how this mount
on the stair railing begins to come loose.
We are maybe thirty people
which holds the railing with all its might.
It was ... Ugh!
But then there was one
which was on the outside of the boat-
-and stretched down
and sort of lifted people up.
We hear it screaming
down in the stairwell.
We try to help and pull up.
It comes up a 10-12 people.
Had you not received help out there
then we would not have gotten anywhere.
And then it almost goes out
all lights out on lifeboat decks.
I see a ship
very far away.
I understand that situation
is very serious.
That it is a matter of life or death.
I decided to
that I do not intend to accept
-that I have to die as a 26-year-old.
"I have not lived my life yet."
"I have to do everything possible
to survive."
Silja Europa, Estonia.
-Estonia, Silja Europa.
- Are you coming to the rescue?
It looks really bad here now.
Really bad.
It is not a question of, but when
you will end up in the water.
Someone has climbed up
and trying to free the lifeboats.
But it is not possible, because the ship is leaning
so much so that the lifeboats remain.
The boat continues to get
even more bias.
So in the end, the boat is basically there
at 90 degrees. You stand on the wall.
I can see the chimney on this
long ship lying down in the water.
And it is completely inconceivable to see.
While lying on the side
so I have time to grab the railing-
-and climb over and out on ships-
side, which becomes like a flat floor.
Then it feels completely unreal.
This is how you can not go on a boat.
It was completely sick.
And we went over the cab windows ...
... and thought we did not want to look
or think about what was in there.
I felt:So scared
I've never been in my whole life.
I feel it in my fingertips
how terribly scared I am.
It is cold and painful. MAN
feel this metal against the body.
I'm only in boxer shorts.
When I sit there and watch
so I see dots ...
Gone on the horizon
so I see ship lights.
I will think about my camera
which I have in my pocket.
I snap off a flash
to signal where I am.
In the photo moment, I see
no one else around me on the ship.
But then when I get the pictures back
and looking at them-
-so I see that it's a person
which sits on the bottom.
Mariella, Silja Europa.
Yes, Mariella here.
Yes, hey. Do you see Estonia?
-No, but I see a red rocket now.
-Yes, it's probably a flare or something.
We see it on our starboard side.
Okay, we'm heading there.
I have an echo on the radar of 50 miles
about, almost straight south of me.
Okay...
That's where the rocket is,
so we have fifty miles left.
The thing is done.
These are very big waves
which washes over the boat.
I think that's about it
as the captain begins to honk.
It's like a signal,
that it's time to leave the ship.
I see two girls in front of us.
One asks the other
if she can hold her hand
-when they go down to the water.
My co-worker, she wanted to
that we would jump into the water.
I said, "No, we have to
have something more to float on. "
"It's cold in the water.
You can't do it for very long. "
And then came these waves
closer and closer all the time.
Finally she said
that we must jump into the water.
Then I took her by the hand,
and so we jumped.
I remember coming down
very far in the water-
-and felt it pull in my pants.
That I was sucked down.
Despite the life jacket and that I swam
as an I-don't-know-what-
-to take me up.
Gets a blow to the head.
Releasing her.
Coming to the surface ...
And she's gone.
I feel pretty fast
that I'm stuck
-and that I'm on my way down with the boat.
I do everything I can to come
loose, but I will not come loose.
And then I think of my mother
and panic.
I think:
"It's not possible. They can not ..."
"Mom and Dad and my sister
can not go to my funeral. "
And I think about everything I learned
in school. Was it unnecessary, as well?
And from Estonia so ... Poff!
A lifeboat is coming up.
They are released at a certain pressure.
So I swim against one like that.
Then we drift away from the ship.
I get very nauseous in the raft
and bends out to vomit.
Then I see the ship sink.
I see the bulb sticking out
high out of the sea. The entire fleet.
It's almost like a church tower
protruding from the sea.
I knock the other man
on the shoulder and pointing at the ship.
Then he looks at it and says:
"There are probably many who are dying now."
All of a sudden I feel
that I have some ropes.
It's all carbon black around me.
After a while, I realize-
-that I ended up
under an upside-down life raft.
Suddenly
so I can hear and feel
-that some are doing
to get to the bottom of the raft.
And I'm eager
to let me know
-because I'm starting to understand
that if there is a rescue operation
-so maybe they forget
that I'm under there.
And I did not want that
that it would happen.
We are slowing down now here.
Mariella slows down. You said something ...
I did not understand what you said.
... we're really close now here.
It's just full of light.
It just seems
as if it were a lot of lifebuoys
and buoy lights around here,
perhaps life rafts.
They're in the lake!
Okay. We are slowly getting closer.
You do not see a boat, do you?
No, there is no boat here.
We discovered quite quickly
that our life raft was upside down.
So we could not get a roof up,
and the water washed over the raft.
I understand that the next threat is
that I can freeze to death.
I also understand that you can
be flushed from the raft.
And I also see that there are several
which it gets late during the night.
Boats are starting to come in
pretty fast-
-who plays with headlights and so on.
We have stopped here now,
and we're really, really close now.
It feels great to know
that you know that this has happened-
-and that help is on the way.
But then I also understand
that it is quite difficult and dangerous.
The risk is that we drive over
a lot of people.
Maybe we should go on the side?
It's hard to see
where to drive in that case.
It's probably just as good to be
in the middle of events and drive away.
We're getting pretty close
Viking Mariella.
People in the raft start screaming
and shout:"Help! Do you see us?"
It was life threatening to a small
rubber raft goes straight into the side
-on this huge boat
or into the propellers.
I thought
that it was very unpleasant.
We do as it is now that we inflate
a pair of rafts and let go in
-if there is anyone
who manage to get hold of them.
Yes, that's the only possibility.
I judge that the weather is so harsh.
It is far from being saved.
I understand that it takes time.
It's a helicopter
on our way here in Turku.
They're picking up your tire,
so prepare the deck for the helicopter.
There will also be two helicopters
from Sweden.
The thing is done.
We are preparing our helicopter deck.
Okay.
We'll finish the helicopter deck.
We acknowledge and make arrangements
the helicopter deck at Symphony.
We must also clarify
the helicopter deck.
-We have the helicopter deck ready too.
-Finemang.
I tremble all night
and freezes terribly
-and my teeth tremble.
Sometime during the night I hear
all of a sudden a death cry.
A long, long, long cry of death
which suddenly falls silent.
And then after that
we hear no more sounds or voices.
It's the only death cry I hear.
-but I remember that forever.
When we sit in the raft at night-
-then there will be a very high wave
so that the roof is pressed down.
It's a man who's panicking.
He shouts that we must have a knife
and cut up the raft.
He's getting more and more confused,
this person.
In the end, he loses consciousness
quite late at night.
I'm grabbing him
and pulls him to me.
I hold him so that the head
is above the water. I think:
"In any case, he should not drown."
In the end, I feel that he
begins to stiffen, that he does not live.
Then I shoot him away from me.
And then he gets to lie there
in the fleet late.
He can stay there. It does not matter.
There are many who lie and float
in the life raft.
There is a fine line
between life and death.
And here there was so little that differed.
When it started to get bright, I am
very tired and very cold.
We sit up to the waist in water,
allihopa.
We've been there
for almost 6.5 hours.
And I'm really tired and sinking
further and further down in the water-
-and I almost fall asleep.
Then I start to think that it is not
some joke to hold on to, but I ...
... let go here
and slides out into the lake.
But then I realize that I have
a nine-month-old Wilma at home.
I have to take care of her. She
need a dad longer than 9 months.
"No, you can not do this!"
"You should do everything you can
to come home again. "
I begin to hear what I interpret
as a helicopter sound, but I think:
"Uh, damn. Some helicopters
does not go out when it is windy like this. "
But it was helicopters.
The wind under the rotor blades is awful.
It's like someone throwing a nail at someone,
with all the water drops hitting.
But still fantastic
to be won over.
When I finally hear helicopters like
stops over us, then it feels like:
"I can no longer bear it.
Now we have to get out of here. "
I was very, very, very tired.
I shout at them, when you hear
the helicopters buzz around there
-that they must not forget
that I'm under there.
And then all of a sudden
then there will be a huge
and we have a helicopter over us.
Then nothing was heard anymore
between us, when we talk.
It's really incredible that someone
has taken a picture of this.
I'm in the middle,
almost naked, in only boxer shorts.
I still do not know
if I will survive.
There I had no strength left.
Of course I'm happy
that this picture was taken
-because you can then see
how terrible this accident was.
That it felt so inhuman that
as a young person you have to give up your life
-and can not say hello then to anyone.
That you can not say goodbye to anyone.
That you are completely alone,
out in the dark, must ...
We have prepared here
to receive people now.
The entire conference department
is prepared.
Yes that is good.
After a while I feel
how it hits the bottom.
It's the lifeguard
which locates where I am somewhere.
After just a little while, he takes
the knife and cuts open the bottom and says:
"It's green. You can come here."
I'm lying and just holding on.
Then finally I pull myself to him
and I get a hug
-the first thing that happens.
Then he puts on my harness,
and we go up.
I'm the one who goes up last.
The joy is total.
It's not up to me anymore.
There are people here
who takes care of me.
I was overjoyed. I was so happy
over having been rescued.
It is strong emotions that come.
It's hard to describe.
We come directly from the area and have
picked up six survivors
and released by them on Utö.
There the fuel had run out ...
Injured, dead
and shocked people-
-introduced to the University Hospital
in Turku.
Here are the helicopters
replaced each other all day.
There are many helicopters in the area.
Six or seven are out there.
And a lot of ships in the area.
But the people who are out there
-are very difficult to cool down,
so it's tough. It is.
And very high lake.
Between six and ten meter waves.
Not everyone will definitely come
to make it.
The last couple of hours
we have only found dead.
But we continue
and trying to find everyone. Thanks.
My colleague...
I asked in the helicopter if they could
provide some information already there-
-but they could not do it.
But only when I got home-
-so I understood that he did not
were among the survivors.
Because they could then have been identified
and named in newspapers and everything.
And then his name came up
among the dead.
Most of the dead
is still down there.
And so is he.
When we started school again
after this
-then it is
a very empty classroom.
We start by refurnishing.
We can not sit
in a standard classroom furniture-
-when there are thirteen benches empty.
On this conference trip
so we were twelve who left Sweden-
-but we were only three
who came back.
Maybe I did not say often enough
how much I loved him.
I said it every now and then, but I did
do not know if I said it enough.
I may not know either
if I was told he was
- such a nice guy as he was.
"Losing your child
is losing its future. "
It writes the Swedish author
Naja Marie Aidt.
When I went to work
September 28 25 years ago
I looked forward to
to once again be able to socialize
-with my active and always equal
curious son of six and a half years.
But that did not happen.
This day 25 years ago
I remember as an unreal nightmare-
- far from reality.
Only a few weeks later
then it dropped in-
-and then reality went
up for me.
It was not a dream-
-but perhaps the most brutal
situation a person can end up in.
Losing a child
- a part of himself.
I would never say more
how much I loved my boy.
I never had time to finish
to answer all your questions-
-or with the task
to be your father.
But all the questions you had,
I take them with me.
Why did Estonia sink?
What happened? Who is responsible?
Hjørund never gave up
until he got an answer.
And neither do I.
I get no peace in my soul
until I get answers to my questions.
Therefore, it must never be quiet
around this disaster-
-until someone can be held accountable
and we relatives get answers.
Estonia capsized and sank
in just a few minutes.
How could this happen?
It is completely unacceptable to over
half a thousand citizens can die
-without even establishing responsibility.
During the 30 years I have
has been a central political
-I have not been with
about such a difficult decision.
Are you thinking of us? How we feel.
What the hell are we going through!
I think they want dark
why the ship sank.
Translation:
iyunomg.com