She weighs only fifty kilos
She must probably be fed with a spoon
That Carita would
start working in Estonia-
- was nothing like us parents
had anticipated.
But she was
trained as a butler.
She had the task of educating
and train Estonian schoolchildren
-to become service-minded
in the right way.
I have to film this.
After turning off the movie camera
you should be beaten.
Carita came home one day and told
-that she had met
a guy named Peter.
He was also of her caliber:
that he was service-minded-
-and worked as a foreman
on board the ship.
Carita and Peter enjoyed traveling.
They had traveled the world
before they married
-to feel that they would
be able to thrive together in need and desire.
Peter told me
that he and Carita-
-had talked a lot
between each other.
Should anything happen on the Baltic Sea
that he or she should die,
how would the other then act?
They had promised each other
to correct the other person's body
-and pick up the body,
unless others did-
-and bury it
in a decent way.
Imagine a government
can counteract such a thing!
You take care of your loved ones
if you can.
I became aware of the disaster
around 05.50 in the morning
-when my clock radio turned on
on the morning prayer.
The search for survivors
from Estonia is now declining.
So far, 70-100 people have ...
Then I understood
that something must have happened.
And then came the news at 6 o'clock.
One of the most devastating
ship accidents ever
-has occurred outside Utö
in the Åboland archipelago.
838 people are still missing-
-after the ferry Estonia
sank in the Baltic Sea last night.
There is a storm in the area, and
extensive rescue work is underway.
And the bulk of the 867 on board
thus followed Estonia in the deep.
Already during the first day,
September 28
-so you understand the extent of the accident.
In the morning we woke up
that the phone rang.
It was a relative who knew about
that Grandma and Bosse-
-had gone to Estonia by ferry.
When I get to the ferry terminal
then I'm met by Peter.
Then Peter and I find out
that Carita probably has not survived.
It is
a terrible information to get.
So it's whole school classes,
groups, workplaces
-who has had employees on
this ship, which has perished.
Society is in shock.
Sadly dressed in a dark suit came
Prime Minister Carl Bildt to Turku.
Here he goes, together
with the Prime Minister of Finland, Esko Aho-
-and Estonian Mart Laar
discuss the rescue operation-
-and the further work
after the ferry disaster last night.
Everyone is anxious about
to find out what has happened-
-and what can be done
to prevent a recurrence.
It is very important to know
what happened on the ferry
-because it's a mystery.
We saw water rushing in
through the door at the front.
-Where did the water come from?
-The door at the front, where the cars drive out.
So water came in through
the front of the ferry? Through the book visor?
At this point
so I was in the engine room.
I saw it
on the camera in the engine room.
Who showed the bow?
And you saw water flowing in?
The cause of the accident
seems to have been
-to the book visor
was not properly closed.
Carl Bildt, it has come to light
information that a hatch on the boat
- should have been open
and thus taken in water.
How do you rate this?
What is the company's responsibility?
It is not my job to judge this,
but the Accident Investigation Board must do so.
This is one thing
for experts to assess.
When the disaster occurred
so we were between two governments.
An outgoing and an incoming,
for it had just been an election.
We had a resigning Prime Minister,
Carl Bildt-
-and we had an incumbent
Prime Minister, Ingvar Carlsson.
Both were asked about
their attitude. How would we do?
How to deal with the dead?
How to handle the ship?
I think we should do
very great effort-
-to save the dead, which of
taking into account not least the
-is something I see
as very, very important.
We have discussed that,
and that work must begin.
I consider all efforts
must be done to get the ship up.
No matter what it costs?
I am prepared to advocate that though
it costs a lot, so let's try.
Everyone wanted it to be investigated
in a constructive and good way.
You have to find out
how this accident could have happened.
Above all, to be able to prevent
-so that similar accidents
does not happen in the future.
Now they would investigate
this accident properly-
and rescue so many dead
and maybe even the ship.
That was it
the immediate, spontaneous thought.
It was completely obvious
and quite naturally, I think.
That you do it after an accident.
And especially this accident,
when there were so many people-
-who did not manage to get out,
but which remained inside the ship.
It felt like the whole community
were set to:
"We have to take care of this
in the right way."
It was something you had to do,
simply.
We relatives were very pleased
when both heads of government say
-that they should do everything that is in
their power to take up the dead.
Then I was filled with hope,
despite all the misery that had happened.
But after a week or so, we realized that
that was probably not really true.
About a week after the accident
so the new government took office.
Then you got a person responsible
to deal with the Estonia disaster:
It was Minister of Communications
Ines Uusmann.
When she started making her statements
so we felt:
"This is not going to be good."
Everything was a problem.
It takes about 28 days
from leaving the water surface
-until you are down with pressure-
chamber to equalize the pressure.
Many people think it is a giant
and complicated surgical
-to do something that has to do with Estonia
to do because she lies so deep.
But it's not deeper than that
if you put Estonia on the high
-so comes over 60 meters
to protrude above the water surface.
That's how shallow it is.
The responsibility that Ines Uusmann was given
was of course very extensive-
-and very difficult
for an inexperienced person to deal with.
So Ines Uusmann became very addicted
by the officials at the Swedish Maritime Administration.
And above all Johan Franson, who
then was chief legal officer at the Swedish Maritime Administration.
He had great influence over it
further the development of the whole issue.
With regard to the ship
lies at a great depth
-and with regard to
that the ship has a fairly large
-so it is, of course
from a technical point of view-
-an extraordinarily demanding task.
Johan Franson had been commissioned
by the government to investigate the possibility
-to rescue wrecks and the dead.
His report, which came
just a few weeks after the disaster
-begins to line up problems
with salvage.
Every diving job
on or in Estonia
-is of course
extremely risky.
Apart from the fact that the diver can get stuck -
a fear that every diver lives with
-so his umbilical cord can be damaged.
He could be injured by life rafts
which suddenly comes loose.
There are lots of shattered glass
which one can cut oneself on.
So there is a big problem,
according to my way of seeing it.
As well as there is one more
normally, major technical problem.
It feels like the change
in reporting
and attitudes about rescuing the dead
and ships immediately began
-then the Swedish Maritime Administration
had been commissioned to investigate.
And that led to the discussions
whether to salvage or not salvage
-started in earnest throughout the country.
Somehow it gets more finished
if you can salvage them-
-and get a funeral
in the usual way.
I have a certain understanding
for the relatives of Estonia.
That they want to pick up their remains
of what was once their family.
I have respect for that.
At the same time, I do not think
-that one should sacrifice more lives, if that
are now considered to be the risks that exist.
This is also the question of:
In what condition are you prepared
-to receive their relatives?
In any condition?
It sounds incredibly cruel,
but this is a catastrophic
- we never like each other
has been near in Sweden.
I think they should stay,
actually.
I do not think it is a special one
nice sight to bring up all the dead.
They are dead, and to me does not mean
a grave so awful much.
Why it became a question
whether to salvage or not salvage?
The first instinct was, after all
that the dead should be taken home.
But then this question arose:
Should you salvage or not salvage?
That it even got to be a question!
Yes, it will be so
that if you do not receive a clear message
-then speculation begins to flourish.
Everything from conspiracy theories
to pure speculation.
One can of course think that it can
have been a Soviet transport
-of some kind of weapon
or explosives or something like that.
And then you start to speculate.
Are they hiding something?
Why in the name of peace
do they not salvage the boat?
Ingvar Carlsson said
that he would do everything in his power
-to get the ship up.
He has not done anything.
-Is it worst not to get a message?
-Yes, that's what you want to know.
The relatives got to meet
Minister of Communications
-The Swedish Maritime Administration, the Danish Council of Ethics, etc.
And it was three hours long
emotional meeting.
Will it be a salvage or not?
That's why I came here
from Hudiksvall.
I've been driving the bus all morning.
Will it be a salvage?
I tamejfan I do not get an answer to that!
The relatives, who represent
all classes of society, had to learn
-how politicians and authorities speak
without giving any straight answers.
-You're not happy with today's ...?
-No no no.
Everything they say
is just to delay
-because we all
should distance themselves from this
-and not require salvage.
It's nothing else.
And for a pressured communication
Minister, it was difficult to explain
-why Ingvar Carlsson
did not line up.
He will surely meet them
repeatedly.
-Why did he not come today?
-He is not at home.
-They have offered to change dates.
-Yes, I can not answer that.
It turned out then gradually
that it capsized over more and more
-from that you would salvage
to not salvage.
And the Swedish government,
for example-
-to dispel anxiety
from relatives and other human
-friends and others concerned
of those who had died
- appointed an ethics council.
Composed more by ethics experts.
No technical experts.
They were quite novices at technology,
so to speak.
But they were a little more, shall we say,
experienced in ethical issues.
The council that was appointed
was commissioned by the government
-to give a recommendation on how to
would do with the salvage of the boat-
-and how to do
with the bodies.
My first thoughts were probably
that it was a trust-
-and that it was good
that they wanted the church to
-and that it was a well-composed one
group that I felt comfortable with.
I thought:
"I can 't say no to this."
"It's a confidence I get
and which I must stand up for. "
Whatever you come up with,
so this hurts people.
It is in the nature of the disaster
-that whatever decisions are made
that's how you hurt people.
Sometimes incredibly bad.
And who do wrong-
-it therefore depends on the outcome
of this process.
So I think
that it is very difficult.
We had to gather a lot of knowledge.
And it was clear that we were pretty
submitted to the knowledge submission-
-because we ourselves
in these matters ...
I have no idea
how to salvage a giant ship
-but I had to trust the pre-
draws we received in the Council of Ethics.
And it's always difficult when you
receives a presentation on a topic
-which you can not.
To be able to ask the right questions.
So it's clear we were extradited
to these reports we received.
In retrospect, we have understood
that the Council of Ethics was completely
-of recommendations
from the Swedish Maritime Administration.
And the same person as before,
then it was Johan Franson-
-which informed the group
about the situation with wrecks and the dead.
Johan Franson was probably quite in favor
not to salvage.
And he was a good debater.
At the time of the disaster in 1994, so be it
I am Sweden's ambassador to Estonia.
And I was asked to participate
in some of the meetings with the Council of Ethics
-to be ... What shall we call
it because? "Estonian expert."
At this first sitting
I was with-
-so was the aforementioned Franson
from the Swedish Maritime Administration
-but also a forensic pathologist
from the National Board of Forensic Medicine.
Then there was the slide show, among other things
from inside the submarine Ulven-
-who went on a mine
during the end of World War II.
And there were pictures shown
with bodies inside the submarine.
It was difficult to take pictures.
There were also oral descriptions-
-of what it would look like
inside Estonia.
With torn furnishings
who had then let go of their mounts.
A pure earthquake-like
landscape inside the ship
and with dead bodies ... pinned,
and so on.
So this was a talk
which lasted quite a long
-and that got us sitting there
to be silent, quite simply.
I think it was relevant.
There is no comparable event-
-in Swedish
moderately modern shipping history.
So I do not think so
that one needs to question.
What was more remarkable
I think
-that it was obvious
that those who preferred
-S Maritime Administration Franson,
forensic pathologists and others ...
It felt clear that they were in
the line to try to avert salvage.
Everything was put together
with the various reports we received.
That it was
such an incredibly much more difficult question
-than we ever
could have imagined us.
It was maybe 800 bodies like man
would try to get out and identify.
What would happen when they came up to
the surface? How long would this take?
What to do with the bodies
in a dignified manner?
How to identify them? We
went through questions at different levels-
-and where an ethical issue was also
not to expose living human beings
-for death
to salvage dead bodies.
It was a clear idea
that it would be a trauma
-for both divers and forensic doctors-
-when so many dead bodies
at the same time would be taken care of.
And that it could lead to
-to permanent mental but
for those involved.
The total reports we received
was that it became so complicated-
-so that it was
almost impossible.
In December 1994
hired Rockwater-
-of the Swedish Maritime Administration for
to examine the wreck after Estonia.
And the purpose was, as far as I understand,
so that the Swedish Maritime Administration
-could decide
whether Estonia could be salvaged or not.
They put together a team. I became
asked to dive in Estonia.
Me and the other divers
had to undergo an examination
-to ensure that we do not
had some trouble diving there-
-because we knew
that there would be corpses there.
The divers' job was actually-
-if you ignore
the tragic aspect and all the victims
-a pretty easy job.
It was not an advanced task.
We arrived at the scene of the accident
and made preparations.
We got a dive plan. We would
enter the cabins under the car tire.
The water depth at Estonia
was actually quite shallow.
I think the bottom was 85 meters.
A freediver can actually hold his breath
and descend to a depth of 85 meters.
We go into the diving bell,
closes it and goes down.
I remember it so clearly, how the hatch
opens when you reach 55 meters.
I looked out. We have a beautiful
lighting system on the outside of the watch.
My first thought was:
"It's crystal clear!"
The view was perfect. You could see
50 meters in front of him. Incredible!
The Baltic Sea may always look like this,
but it was amazing.
Estonia was an incomparable sight from above.
Beautiful, white ...
The keel was completely flawless,
as if the ship had just been launched.
We could see that it did not exist
some wreckage in the road
-so we moved the dive clock-
-to the place where we were going
cut us into the cabins.
It was reinforcing steel.
I managed to make a small hole-
-and listed in,
but I saw nothing in there.
I made the hole bigger and stuck in
hand to see if I felt anything.
Then I widened the hole
so that I could get in.
Okay, are you ready?
-We are ready when you are ready.
-Okay.
We went into the cabins under the deck.
Okay.
I'm outside the first cab.
We just wanted to see
if there was anyone in the cab.
-Okay. I'm opened the door.
-Okay.
I went into the first cab.
It was easy.
The cabins under deck were very small.
The question was:
"Stewart, can you see anything in the cabin?"
The visibility was perfectly okay.
But once I got in
then everything started to whirl up.
I feel like it's a body
next to me, but I can not see it.
-Can you feel a body next to you?
-Yes.
Okay. There is a body there ...
- Keep going, just.
-Roger.
We did not swim around inside
in Estonia and did as we pleased.
There were government officials on board.
They told us exactly where we were going
and what we would look for.
Just below you on the right
so I think there is a body.
-Yes, there are two bodies here.
-Is there two bodies there?
That's right.
Is it possible to take a close-up
which the doctor can get?
Our job was to follow orders.
They said to us, "Look here,
look over there. Look in the next cab. "
"If you come across a corpse,
be respectful and move on. "
"That's all you have to do."
What I want you to do is
to approach one of the bodies.
Take a picture of your face
with your helmet camera.
-Do you see?
-No.
Do you see now, then?
-The only thing I see is hair, really.
-Okay.
Should I lift it up
and turn it over?
Yes, if you can.
Okay. We've seen enough. Thanks.
Between dives,
when the guys came up from a
-so we talked about
what we had seen and done.
Some of the guys
searched in areas where it ...
There were dead everywhere.
So another body
on the other side of the door?
-Oh, there are lots of them!
-Yes.
-Okay. Are you doing well?
When we dived inside the shopping area ...
There were many bodies in there.
People had become trapped when they
tried to get out through the doors.
Some had run out of the cab
in just a bathrobe.
In fact, they still were
in relatively good condition.
Some wore lipstick -
as fine as two months earlier.
We passed them, one by one.
But all the time they thought:
"We are here now.
Why do we not just address them? "
-Are the bodies to your right?
-Yes.
-Okay. Continue on, just.
-Roger.
That we would not take up
the bodies ... It was outrageous.
We divers could have picked them up
in a few hours.
There had been no problem.
There were no practical obstacles
against taking up the bodies.
You put it in a body bag, you put it
it in the basket and lifts it up.
It may sound a little cynical-
-but this is how it works in practice:
Coffin - basket - hoist up to the surface.
But that was not our job.
We just needed a basket.
The authorities could have flown there
a forensic pathologist, if needed.
A phone call would have been enough:
"Yes, take up the bodies."
Why was it not said that way?
We were shocked.
Our conclusion then was that a large
number of bodies could have been taken up.
We located 125 victims
and documented them in the reports.
Of course we could have found more,
if that had been the goal.
Of course, there are not many
in relation to 852 deaths
-but there are still many.
We also reported that the ship,
in our opinion, could be salvaged.
It would undeniably
have been complicated-
-but we still considered
that it could be salvaged.
Prime Minister Ingvar Carlsson
now provides information
-on the issue of salvage
of Estonia.
The issue of salvage
or not salvage-
-can be assessed
from different starting points.
There are all the practical problems
and the ethical issues.
But there is also
the wishes of individuals.
Relatives who each in their own way
mourns their loved ones.
Therefore, there is now no reason
to delay a decision.
The relatives and everyone else
has the right to
-even if it will be received
with the despair of some.
The Swedish Government's decision
-to the passenger ferry M / S Estonia
with the dead shall remain in the sea.
This afternoon decided
the Swedish government
-that the accident vessel should remain
on the seabed forever.
There is no financial
or technical reasons behind the
-without ethical values.
During the 30 years I have been
central political activity
-I have not been to one
so painful and such a difficult decision.
In the autumn, Ingvar Carlsson promised
that Estonia would be saved.
He apologizes for that today.
Had I known then what I know now-
-I would not
have pronounced me that way.
How can you as head of government-
- betray a promise
to behave civilly?
It's something you can not understand.
I'm hugely disappointed and pissed
because it turned out the way it did.
When the decision came
that they would not salvage the Estonian
-that's how it felt
as if the whole house of cards collapsed.
It feels like it's coming
a wall directly opposite you.
Someone said we would not salvage them
because we would be traumatized.
But it was more traumatic
to leave the bodies there.
25 years later we are still talking
about Estonia, and everyone wonders:Why?
It was a difficult decision to make,
and we knew from the beginning that many
-would be relieved, and many
would think it was the wrong decision.
I have a big pile of thank you letters-
-and I also have a pile of letters
where one thinks the decision was wrong.
I always had the feeling of
that the government and the
and the Council of Ethics
and those who conducted the
-done based on their starting points
as best they could ever.
Then the human is enough
not always to.
And we can make mistakes, even though we
have done the best we could.
I think the authorities
acting in general
in the case of Estonia,
has been completely insane.
And what will happen next
is even worse.
The place where M / S Estonia sank
shall be considered a burial site.
To ensure
that grave peace is respected
-shall the ship be covered
and special measures are taken
-to provide the burial site
legal protection.
Estonia will be covered
with stone or concrete
-to prevent grave looting.
We cover Estonia
for all the human
-who has felt a concern
for wreck looting.
There was
large amounts of alcohol on the boat.
The dead may have been wearing jewelry.
It was an awfully unpleasant thought-
-that strangers would
touch the dead bodies in the boat.
It was such an unpleasant thought.
But even if the decision has now been made
so the debate does not
-and the many perceptions
around the country's biggest disaster.
It has never before in history
put forward such an idea-
-like casting a ship
and all perished in concrete.
It's a senseless idea.
Why do you present such an idea?
It was a hostile atmosphere
at the meeting-
-between the relatives
to the Estonian Offen-
and representatives of the government
and authorities.
What is crucial, I think,
is that from the very beginning
-try to show respect
also for government decisions.
You talked about respect.
I think it's disrespectful
to cast people in concrete.
This would never happen
have happened in Norway!
We must not leave
a large group of relatives
-which will cause mental suffering
the rest of his life
-dependent on something
which happened after the disaster.
Every time I go to the cemetery
and looking at the memorial stone-
-and see the poem on the stone, I know
that Hjørund should have been here.
A piece of Hjørund should be here.
I still feel hope.
Hope he
to be taken up from the Baltic Sea.
Or that which one can find
can be taken up from the Baltic Sea.
I hope so.
It should have been done a long time ago,
but it may never be too late.
When Peter gets ready for himself-
-that the government does not
will address the fatalities
-then a thought is born in him:
"I have to arrange this myself."
Peter started planning this
action in January, February 1995-
-because he could not accept
this concrete shell.
He had made his promise to
Carita. He would live up to that.
It must be done legally.
And then it must happen
before the peace of peace came into force.
He had received insurance money,
so he could afford
-to cost on this operation.
With the help of a German boat
-so he could go
to the sinking site.
He had managed to get the right ones
the coordinates of finding the ship.
Then he would with the help of
and s.k. ROV take up Carita's body.
Peter had spoken
with Carita's surviving friends.
They had told me
what her end looked like.
And he knew exactly
was it was somewhere.
He had worked on the ship himself
and knew very well what it looked like.
So there were no problems at all
to try to find her.
And so this is the days before
the Tomb Peace Act enters into force.
So it's okay to go out.
But what happened was
that since the Swedish government
- knew about his expedition,
so they sent out an icebreaker.
Fairplay VII.
This is the icebreaker Ale.
This area is
according to Swedish, Finnish and Estonian
-the last resting place
for the victims on board the Estonia ferry.
Can you respect that
and leave the area? Come on.
Imagine a government
can counteract such a thing!
Fairplay VII, Fairplay VII.
Do not lower any equipment
for photography or the like.
I will call
the Finnish Coast Guard
-and inform them
about your intentions. Come on.
Then Ale gets there
and make waves like this.
It is completely forbidden
according to international law.
So they can not do this
the attempt to take up Carita's body.
So he had to give up this attempt.
I thought I was a citizen
in a civilized country.
But apparently I'm not,
because the state does not want to take
-about their citizens.
I think that about Carita's body
had been reimbursed
and we had to bury her
in the grave we have-
-and where Peter is alone now,
then it would have meant peace for us.
We could have moved on in this life
and thinks that:
"It was awful,
what happened"-
- "but we have in any case
brought home her body "-
- "and been able to bury it
in a decent way. "
Late last night
came the special vessel Tertnes
-to the place where Estonia sank,
with ten thousand tons of crushed stone.
Today, the crew has measured out
exactly where Estonia is located.
Tomorrow morning
if you start emptying the cargo
-to strengthen the seabed
around the wreck.
As a normal person who thinks,
so it is completely illogical-
-that you cover a ship with concrete
after an accident.
If it was a completely normal accident.
What did the authorities get
to make these decisions
-so completely opposite
against what you normally do?
You do not know
if this was really an accident.
It may actually have been
something else that happened out there.
To me, it seems that man
tried to hide something with it all.
The only thing I know is that Hjørund
is located somewhere in the Baltic Sea.
But no one tells
why he's lying there.
They just picked up the bow visor.
But that does not say much.
It just fell off. Why
in all peace they do not salvage the boat?
Are they hiding something?
The investigation has not been able to explain
why Estonia sank so fast.
Water came in on car tires,
and then the ferry sank.
There is no explanation
to why it sank.
It feels like you
has skipped a bit.
"The bow visor comes loose,
water enters the car tire "-
- "which lowers the ship."
What a ship should do then
-according to physical laws,
is to capsize.
And then they point to Jan Heweliusz.
She capsized.
She floated for a week or so.
For the ship to sink, it must
air mass is displaced by water.
So there must be
some kind of cavity-
-or openings in the ship
which causes it to sink.
The researchers say:
"I have never been" -
- "that a ship such as Estonia
drops so fast "-
- "if there has not been a hole
below the waterline. "
And it is not even investigated!
Why is it like that?
Why has it not been done?
What do you want to hide?
What do you not want?
let come?