Estonia is not
any accident.
It is an extremely pervasive
and serious accident
-with very many victims
and many, many concerned.
And in a state governed by the rule of law
-so you have to do everything to apply
the truth about such an accident.
There must not even be a suspicion
about trying to hide something-
-or trying to keep something secret.
Decision of 15 December 1994
came as a cold shower.
Then came the rather macabre idea
to cover the ship
-with a concrete sarcophagus-
-which has never happened before
in any context.
It's a strange decision.
300 million taxpayer money for
disappears from the unemployment insurance fund and child allowance
-which you throw into the lake,
that no one wants.
To me, that is completely illogical
to cover the ship with concrete
-if it was a common accident.
That's disrespectful
to cast people in concrete.
This had never happened in Norway!
It seemed to me
as one tried to hide something.
You do not know about this
really was an accident.
What is it that is so secret when one
civilian passenger ship in peacetime
-travels in peaceful waters
and have an accident?
Why it must be circumvented
with so many secret stamps etc?
A state governed by the rule of law
leaves no effort unscathed
-to find out
what really happened.
Nordica, then we play home.
We have a heavy load in the tire stack.
Slowly comes the book visor
up to the surface.
The bow visor hangs upside down
and is ill-advised.
The force that knocked it off
must have been huge.
The book visor was located
about two kilometers west of the wreck.
This means that the ship has been turned over
after the visor has come off
-for not take in water.
But how quickly after the crash
can not yet be said.
Now that you basically know the reason
will you take even more action?
We mean we very quickly
must write a full report
-where we describe a little more fully
what we have technically been able to establish.
In December 1994, they knew
that the bow visor had come loose.
Witnesses had seen
that the bow visor was gone.
If the bow visor had come loose, it must
the locking devices have given way.
Let's test the rebar
withstands the pressure.
Our calculations were important to
find out why this happened.
We managed to break it!
What had happened
was obvious from the beginning.
Here we have
Accident Investigation Board Report.
It describes what they thought happened
out on the Baltic Sea
the night of September 28, 1994.
On 228 pages
the official answers
-on why the Baltic ferry sank-
-the stormy September night1994.
The answer to the question of why Estonia
bow visor came loose and she capsized
-will be reported.
They worked for several years to come
until these conclusions.
We felt it was a bit close
to search for answers
-on things like you already are
had stated from the beginning.
The locking mechanism
on the bow visor was too weak.
The ramp was forced down due to
mechanical impact of the bow visor.
When the official
Accident Investigation Board, JAIC-
- "Joint Accident
Investigation Commission "-
report came, 1997 in the autumn-
-was my reaction:
"Well, was that how it went?"
"Okay. I'm not an accident investigator."
I could neither say no nor beg.
But there were others
who were better experts than I-
-and who reacted quite quickly
and who contacted us then
members of the Riksdag, and said:
"This is not true."
It contains various maps,
what happened in different places-
-which ships were nearby.
It describes in detail
how the sinking process went
-according to the Accident Investigation Board
perception.
"September 27, 1994, 7:15 p.m.:
Estonia is leaving the port of Tallinn. "
"The boat is about 15 minutes late."
"The weather report that is read out
on the radio just over an hour before departure "-
- "warns of storm
up to 21 meters per second. "
"00.55:first bang."
"The ship is hit by a big wave" -
- "and it is heard
a metallic bang from the bow.
"01.00:
The book visor locking device is missing. "
"Several passengers
and crew members "-
- "hears an abnormal noise
for ten minutes."
"Estonia continues
at the same speed as before. "
"01.14:The ship has no list.
The book visor falls off. "
"The ramp inside falls down" -
- "large amounts of water flow in
and upsets the balance. "
"The ship gets a heavy list."
"In about a minute it's gone
0 to 15 degrees to starboard. "
"The commander on the bridge
trying to save the situation "-
- "by steering upwind
and turn port. "
"01.20:The engines stop.
The impact side is 30 degrees. "
"The ship is taking in
20 tonnes of water per second. "
"01.24:Estonia calls mayday."
Mayday, mayday!
"Answered by MS Silja Europa."
This is Silja Europa.
Did you make a mayday call?
"01.25:The strike side is appreciated
to more than 40 degrees starboard. "
"01.29:60 degree tilt."
Silja Europa, Estonia!
"The last radio message
from Estonia is intercepted. "
"Really bad,
it looks really bad here now "-
- "shouts the third mate
Andres Tammes. "
"01.35:The ship capsizes.
The impact side is 80 degrees. "
"01.40:The impact side is 140 degrees."
"01.50:Estonia drops."
"Estonia perishes in the moonlight
and disappears from the radar screens "-
- "about 55 minutes
after the first blow. "
"The final
holding on to the hull "-
- "ends up in the water
or be dragged down into the depths. "
Very detailed report
-but unfortunately it probably is not
what happened.
A ship of that size
does not sink that way so fast.
If there was no other reason
to why water came into the boat.
It was established early on that the bow visor
was to blame for it all.
So that was a conclusion
which was completed
-already when the Accident Investigation Board
started working.
Then they spent three years
to confirm that conclusion.
You did it that way
disregarded all testimonies-
-and all other circumstances
who could speak against that conclusion.
It is, of course, quite the opposite-
-how it should go
in a serious accident investigation.
The Accident Investigation Board did not carry out any
systematic interrogations with survivors.
I've never been a part
of any survey.
You make a declaration of sea.
They can testify
how the ship behaved and sank
-and what they saw and did not see.
I mean the report
and the investigation that has taken place
-not at all illuminating
what has really happened.
The only thing I was questioned about
the accident was after a week in Sweden.
Then the police contacted me and
I gave them a testimony.
I was never allowed to talk to anyone
at the Accident Investigation Board.
The interview was conducted by telephone.
No one called a second, third or
fourth time from the Swedish police.
When I read the minutes today-
-I see almost in every sentence
something that has been misunderstood.
When you immerse yourself in the material
Can you see-
-that one person was considered a witness
for he belonged to the crew.
I, as a passenger,
has not been considered a witness.
Wouldn't they be worth it
to attach faith to?
Do you have that perception
so I think you are wrong.
The battle began
at midnight Swedish time.
While the Accident Investigation Board
says a quarter later.
This is a unique
documents from Estonia.
It's my watch
which I put in my pocket.
Set in Swedish time,
shows when the tilt began-
-because it has just stopped
after twelve o'clock.
That was when it fell to the floor
and the battery fell out.
So the clock stopped then.
I know the clock should have been around
twelve at night because I heard a beep.
A digital clock that beeps somewhere.
A little after twelve
bangs two very powerful bangs.
I thought we might have gone
Because. That was my first thought.
Right on that, my bunk started to tilt.
It tilts like this at once.
And the slope remains.
"01.00:The ship has no list."
The battle side came very quickly.
That went quick.
It's like the bed is getting up.
Then I get dressed.
I'm trying to open the door,
where all my luggage fell down.
Then I feel on the floor
at the door if there is anything more.
Then I find my alarm clock
which I put in my pocket.
I just do that
so that I can open the door
-without getting stuck in anything.
Because it opens inwards.
I decide to get dressed
and go out and see what happens.
When I get a bit up the stairs,
then it begins to carve in the ship-
-and I wonder
what's going on.
"Several passengers
and crew members "-
- "hears an abnormal noise
for 10 minutes. "
"The ship has no list."
All loose equipment
went over to the starboard side.
There was stuff on the diagonal.
The battle side is all the time
jerkily worse.
I feel that it is not going well.
It's not heading in the right direction.
"Estonia continues at the same pace.
The ship has no list. "
When I get up the stairs,
tilts the ship to further.
I have to grab the stair railing
to keep me going.
Many lose their grip.
Then you lose your footing and go
slide towards the other end of the boat.
Pretty soon after that
then comes a Coca Cola machine.
It has dropped from the wall.
Now the ship is leaning so much
that you can stand with one foot on the deck
-and one foot on the wall.
You stand as at the bottom of a "V".
01:14:
The ship has no list. "
It has gone on appreciatively
5-10 minutes.
This is something that is not true.
We who survived had compiled
a period of time together
-as we agreed.
We met at Ersta and left
through this together.
We arrived at
that we had a very similar view-
-about when things happened.
"I remember,
I was there, I was there ... "
Everything fell into place
and it did not agree
-how it was described
in the accident report.
That's why we started acting,
write a letter.
We were 34
who signed it.
We requested
to get a renewed investigation.
An accident commission exists
to find out the cause of an accident.
I'm still convinced
that there are
-in the Accident Investigation Board's report.
Everything can be criticized.
Everyone can criticize.
The cause of the accident
was clear to us.
The Accident Investigation Board's theory
why Estonia sank
-was first to hit the visor
away from the shoulder.
Thereafter, the bow ramp falls down
and huge amounts of water
enters the open deck.
The Accident Investigation Board's theory is that
the water caused the boat to sink.
The book visor comes loose
- water enters the car tire
which sinks the ship.
What a ship should do then
according to physical laws is to capsize.
When boats capsize fast,
this is how air pockets arise
-which gives the boat buoyancy.
When ships are upside down
-can they stay very fluid
long thanks to the air in the hull.
The big unanswered question-
-is why she did not tip completely around
and lay and floated very long-
-as had happened
the ferry Jan Heweliusz the year before
-which got tilted,
and immediately turned 180 degrees around
-and lay for 24 hours
and floated that way.
Estonia sank in less than an hour.
How could water come down
under car tires so fast?
It can not be explained by
that the water came only from car tires.
There are those who claim
have seen water under car tires.
Nobody has asked us, they say.
Other than a few,
who have been interrogated.
My cab is under the car deck.
When I get around the corner-
-I see that there will be water,
which rushes in along the wall.
There are such quantities
that I understand at once-
-that it is seawater
who have entered the ship.
The water I see
when I get out of my cab
-I wonder where it comes from.
I can not understand why it would
be water inside the corridor-
-in a boat under the car deck.
Even today, I can not understand
-how the explanation can be
that the bow visor was removed
-if I saw water coming at the bottom-
and not from the stairs where I ran
up, but along the wall.
The water came into the basement-
-from a completely different path
than the one I ran up.
No one denies
that the bow visor has come loose.
But that was not the reason
until the ship sank.
September 28, 1994
I worked in Berlin.
I worked as
investigative reporter on Spiegel TV.
I became suspicious
against the Accident Investigation Board
the way they behaved, what they
arrived at and reported on the
-when I interviewed
two key witnesses.
Henrik Sillaste and Tanel Moosaar were
two technicians who worked in Estonia.
They were the last two to get out,
via the chimney.
Water also flowed there
when they climbed out.
They came out at the last minute.
We asked to interview them.
What we wanted to know
was what they had seen.
From the control room
-could they see via a camera
which was aimed at the bow ramp.
They looked all the way through the camera
to that the ship tilted 90 degrees.
They drew a picture for us.
Can you draw it?
They could see the ramp
from the control room via a camera.
It was never open.
Only small amounts of water
which came in on the pages-
-but not large enough quantities
to sink the ship.
This goes against
The Accident Investigation Board's theory.
If the ramp was never open
-we must determine how water
flowed in so that Estonia sank.
Estonia was built in the German Meyer-
yard, which is still in operation today.
Of course they wanted to defend themselves,
so they called in a group of experts
shipbuilders,
captains and lawyers
-who were specialists in the field.
This is car tire on Estonia,
seen from the center and forward.
Here is the bow ramp,
here is the center party.
Port side.
They made their own calculations
and collected testimonies.
For example, testimonies from all of them
who lived in the cabins under the car tire.
There are indications that
this section was filled with water
-and was under pressure
when the ship leaned to starboard.
The Meyer shipyard came to the conclusion-
-that water must have flowed in
from elsewhere.
Not via car tires, but under it.
For them, it really exists
just an explanation for this.
There was a hole in the hull
on starboard side-
-the same side to which the ships are leaning.
This hole is probably
the main reason why the ship sank.
That's right
with what really happened.
After almost five years of work,
Meyer Shipyard finalizes its final report
and explanation of
why Estonia perished.
The conclusions
are controversial to say the least.
The Meyer shipyard claims that it existed
several explosive charges on Estonia
-which detonated during the disaster.
Someone placed according to the yard
experts, explosives on board
-which detonated
in connection with the boat sinking.
The report states that
that part of the damage
-caused by explosions.
-And it says so in the final report?
-Yes, everything is there.
-Who placed the explosive there?
-I do not know.
Those who did
wanted to sink the ship.
Werner Hummel points out that
the explosions are not the main cause
-but has accelerated the process.
Christer Lindvall, you are
CEO of the Swedish Shipowners' Association.
-And you have been running Silja Line for ten years?
-Yes it is true.
- Do you believe in this information?
-As for the explosion part ...
... I want to say
that it sounds strange.
But I have had the highest confidence in it
Meyer shipyard's previous investigations.
And also the chief prosecutor in Stockholm
has taken both the Accident Investigation Board
and the Meyer shipyard report
and equalized
-and said that both
the course of events is probable.
I think it's important to
get the whole ship examined.
It's on the page,
so it can be difficult
-to examine that page
which lies towards the bottom.
But as long as this kind of speculation
will emerge
-so I see it as necessary to
that we get a new accident commission.
I'm sure we're here
up to the actual cause-
and the facts.
All other causes
or theories are not ...
They do not deserve
to be taken seriously.
We did a standard survey-
-to see if the ship could be salvaged.
Then you have to know
the condition of the vessel. We found out.
We examined the entire ship
with an underwater robot.
Condition of the vessel,
apart from the
-the absent bow visor
and the ramp, was perfect.
The only
serious injuries we could see
-was on the bow visor and the ramp.
That you dived those first times-
- we do not know there
what one was looking for at all.
It is not known if the entire ship was gone
through and documented on film.
There are pictures that have disappeared,
which one cannot see.
Videos, etc. as of different
unknown reasons just do not exist-
-has disappeared.
Why? Why has
the documentation disappeared?
What are the reasons for that?
It is alleged that the wreck was examined
-but we have not seen
any documentation on it.
There are no reports
that the wreck has been examined
-and that it
has given a certain result.
We filmed a lot and we
thought that was enough.
But we did not film systematically.
We had no reason to do so.
Because we did not expect
to find any damage to the hull.
Our mission was not
to find the cause of the accident.
But it was very clear
what was the cause.
It was the book visor.
The bow visor and the ramp.
That was the reason.
Water in the ship, the ship capsizes.
As simple as that.
With a ro-ro ship
is it that simple.
We must remember that this is
quite difficult things to understand
-and you do not understand
on such things-
- maybe you should not either
poking its nose into.
They get excited
completely without reason-
-and they are reminded of their grief
and tears up his wounds.
Does that really make sense?
I do not know what I do.
It is unreasonable that so many do not know
what happened to even loved ones.
I know how it feels.
I lost my parents
when I was 21 years old.
They died in an accident.
At that time I was
very important
-to find out what had happened.
I was glad I could
go to a grave to mourn.
I can only imagine
how it must have felt
-to be left in uncertainty
of the rulers of their own country
-and not get a real explanation.
"The ship sank,
your loved ones are gone. "
"Shut up
and move on with your life. "
This is not how the government in a country should be
treat their citizens.
Seminar participants, speakers
- a brief information:
We have posted a piece of paper
out in the foyer that we ask you to read.
If you sympathize with the content
you are welcome to sign.
In 2000, a conference was organized
on the Estonia disaster
-in Stockholm by the relatives.
I participated in the hope
to perhaps get new information.
There I met
American Gregg Bemis.
I've spent most of it
of my life at sea.
I am also chairman of the board
in two companies.
One is perhaps the largest in the world
commercial diving school.
The second is called
Deep Ocean Engineering-
-and has probably made more sub-
water robots than any other company.
Gregg had great experience
of diving on wreckage
-and wanted to do it too
on the Estonia wreck.
Our goal was to find and film
the hole that must be in the hull.
We are looking for the mentioned hole
at the bottom of the ship.
That's the easiest way
to describe it.
Gregg Bemis and his diving team
should look for holes in the hull
-and thus try to prove it
was not just a detached bow visor
-which caused Estonia to sink,
which the Accident Investigation Board has claimed.
I think we can find what we are looking for
in four days.
The goal is to find evidence of that
needs a new investigation.
What do you think you will find?
I think we will find others
reasons why the ship sank
-which does not correspond to what
is stated in the Accident Investigation Board's report.
For the first time in several years is
divers on their way down to Estonia's wreck.
We had announced our plans.
When we arrived at the place it was
as if the circus had come to town.
There were press boats everywhere.
The Finnish and
the Swedish coastguard was there.
They tried to persuade us
not to dive.
One Eagle, what are your intentions?
To do my job - just like you.
We have to agree
about how we should behave towards each other.
I have to inform you about
-that according to Swedish law it is not
allowed to dive in this place.
Seven countries around the Baltic Sea have written
on the Agreement on Peace in Estonia.
Which means diving
at the ship are prohibited.
But the United States has not signed the agreement.
They should help us.
They have nothing to lose on it.
Either they get
his own report confirmed
-or they realize it exists
need for further investigations.
Do they have nothing to hide-
should they be interested
of finding more evidence.
During the operation
-come both the Swedish
and the Finnish Coast Guard on board.
It was like in a movie.
People came on board and
tried to threaten us while we were filming.
It is a crime in Sweden.
If you were to visit Sweden
on holiday or in another matter-
-there is a risk
that the police are involved.
It was completely unreal.
It is international waters.
What we did
was to try to find the truth.
What would a possible new inspection
of the starboard side could lead to?
It could possibly be off
value in being able to remove
-some of the rumors about
a large hole on the starboard side.
Early in our expedition
we tried to find the big hole.
But it was so clear
large piles of stone and sand
-exactly in that place.
We did not have the opportunity
to remove it.
It would have required resources
which we did not have access to.
But we found a hole.
-Are you kidding me?
-No, this is not a joke!
Gregg! We've found the hole.
It looks small. Someone has tried
cover it with sand.
The sand sinks
all the time down the hole-
-but the top part
is still visible.
All that is needed is a small hole.
We can not say anything about the size,
then we only see a little bit of it.
That's all we need. It is enough
to launch a new investigation.
An American-German diving expedition
claims that their
new film footage of Estonia's wreck
-shows one so far
unknown hole in the hull.
But after reviewing the film
in a TV studio in Tallinn today
-beats Finnish representatives
for the Accident Investigation Board back.
If there was a hole there
the sand would not have been like that.
Then the sand would have been sucked in
through the hole.
That there would be a hole there
I see as completely impossible.
Swedish experts believe that there is a hole
one claims to have found is a scam.
They apparently found no holes.
They searched very carefully and knew what
they were looking for. They found no holes.
He has failed
with the assignment he undertook.
He said:"I can point to a hole.
I am convinced that it exists. "
When he has not done, I think man
will say:"Thank you and hello, Mr. Bemis."
"You have not succeeded
with this mission. "
"Hereby
you are no longer interesting. "
I do not believe in
Conclusion of the Accident Investigation Board.
For me, it has all the time
been impossible to believe that ...
That a ship
must be covered with concrete
-if it is a completely normal accident.
There must be another reason.
I moved to Estonia in 1995.
Then I got a visit
by a Finnish lawyer
-who worked for the shipyard
who had built the ship Estonia.
Of course, they were looking for
opportunities to perhaps find
-some reason for the accident
so that they do not become guilty.
They had read reports,
I told them my story.
And...
They asked many questions-
-but a question,
which I could not forget-
-which seemed to be very important ...
They asked me
about what I saw in the water.
If it could be a submarine.
A little after twelve it slams
giant bangs.
It sounds like the fart
goes through ice.
I rush straight up the stairs.
I would think that I
in just a few seconds
-from the fact that I hear the strange
the sound in the cab until I catch up.
I do not think it took a minute even-
-until I got up
to the last floor of the ship.
When I get out of the ship
I do not see any people.
Where I stand there are no people.
I was one of the first to get there.
When I stand there
I look out to sea.
I look down and then I see
something strange in the water.
I see something white that is
several times several meters large.
Moving to the left.
This was moving.
I never did
military service.
I have no idea
what submarines look like in the water.
It was dark in the water.
I have no idea about a submarine
may look brighter than water.
But obviously
drove the ship on something
-for what is it that explains
that you hear sound
-which sounds like that ship
drive through ice
-when you are down there where you hear
everything that hits the ship?
With such big events
you have to be extra careful.
You have to be extra careful
with what you write and report
-and do not speculate.
When searching online
why Estonia sank
-you can find all possible
kind of conspiracy theories.
Some are very odd and unlikely.
Some claim that Arabs were behind it,
that Israel did
-or that it was about
drug smuggling that went awry.
This makes it difficult for serious on-call
nalister. Because when you hear
-clump together with the others
the conspiracy theorists.
No one knows what to believe.
But after researching
The 21-year-old Estonia accident
-I have come to this conclusion:
Estonia was used for transportation
important information-
-from Russia to the West.
It's about the Russian mafia,
smuggling-
and other criminal activity.
It was a collaboration between MI6-
Estonian intelligence service and
the Swedish intelligence service.
There were two clear warnings
from Russia to the West.
"We know what you're smuggling
aboard Estonia. "
"You have to stop, otherwise ..."