My name is Stephen Davis
and is a journalist.
I'm from New Zealand,
but I have worked all over the world.
I have explored many phenomena,
but they all have one thing in common:
Authorities, companies and influential
people who obscure things.
That which drives me
are the people you talk to
-which has been fed with lies
or have not received any
-and as desperate
searching for the truth.
It was obvious that the facts were obscured
in the aftermath of the Estonian disaster.
During my review of the incident-
-I discovered it existed
an agreement regarding the burial site.
All three governments,
Estonia, Finland and Sweden
-agree that we should
consider this a graveyard.
Because it's that way, it is
criminal to go down to the wreck.
The agreement was signed
of the countries around the Baltic
-as well as the UK, odd enough.
The UK is not located
on the Baltic Sea.
That's pretty weird
that they signed the agreement.
I contacted the British to take
find out why the agreement was signed
-and got cold hand.
Why did the British sign an agreement?
that hindered the exploration of the ferry?
We'll take a closer look
on Richard Tomlinson.
The boy from Ngruawhia who became
spy and ended up as a nationless.
He lives in exile in the south of France
-can not return to New Zealand,
and is wanted in the UK.
MY LIFE AS A SPY
Richard Tomlinson
was an MI6 agent who was fired
- under mysterious circumstances.
Are they afraid of what you can reveal?
The thing has grown bigger and bigger-
-in the media, the public
and, worse, the eyes of the police.
He carried many secrets,
but would he really reveal them?
But the British action
made him angry and upset
-and he had something
to tell me.
Tomlinson had a New Zealand passport.
He was born in New Zealand.
We arranged
so that he could go to Paris
-and fly to Auckland with his
New Zealand passport to meet me.
He said, "Did you know about this?"
He produced a document
and handed it to me.
It traded
on the sinking of Estonia.
"Do you know this?"
And I answered:
"Yes, I know that,
but are you really involved? "
He said, "You should check this out."
"We were involved
in a smuggling operation in Estonia. "
"There are hidden facts here,
and you should investigate. "
I asked if "we" meant MI6,
and he answered yes.
After 6.5 years in power confirmed
Mikhail Gorbachev resigned tonight.
The symbol of the Soviet regime was removed.
The red flag
was replaced by the Russian
- when Mikhail Gorbachev officially
became the last leader of the Soviet Union.
I was lucky enough to grow up
at the same time-
-as Estonia
regained its independence.
It was like a fever.
People were euphoric.
The most symbol-laden event
was the formation of the human chain.
The chain started in Tallinn and stretched
all the way to the capital of Lithuania.
To call it a big event
is an understatement.
It's called the singing
revolution because of the mass rallies
-under which hundreds of thousands
people sang together.
We had recaptured our place
on the map and was taken seriously.
We had regained power
over our own country.
In 1991 I was appointed Swedish
-and not only Sweden's, but it
the very first ambassador to Estonia
-which a few days before had
restored its independence.
The country was dependent on ferry traffic.
Demand, both
at passenger and car seats-
-became bigger than you could offer.
A new ship was needed, and
it was named after Estonia.
The ship was absolutely crucial to that
Estonia got up so quickly.
Many people had their first meeting
with the Western world aboard Estonia.
Many saw oysters and pineapples
for the first time on the buffet table.
They boarded the Estonia
and at the same time stepped into the western world
and capitalist society.
That ship
was named after Estonia, Estonia-
-shows how important the ship was
for Estonia.
After
the liberation of the Baltic States
- the Soviet bases were wound up.
That meant a lot of weapons
and military materiel
-of Soviet and Russian origin
would suddenly be moved-
-and very much came into operation.
It was described as the "Wild West".
It was sold, it was bought,
it was taken out of the country.
There was no control over
where the weapons and materiel went.
The situation was that
that Swedish and Western interests
-also was looking to get over
the Soviet systems and weapons.
When the Estonians became independent
they wondered how long freedom would last
persisted and asked the western world for help.
They wanted the western world to
protect them from Russia.
They prioritized formation
of a good intelligence service.
They asked MI6 for help with the establishment
of this new intelligence service.
MI6 has had strong ties for a long time
the Swedish intelligence service.
Therefore, it was natural that Sweden
and Estonia cooperated with MI6.
Equipment was shipped from Russia
across the border into Estonia.
It was taken to the port, loaded
on ships and shipped to Sweden.
It was a very successful route
which was used for many years.
The Estonian flagged passenger ferry
Estonia with 867 people on board
-sunk last night, southwest of Finnish Utö.
Estonia capsized and sank on some
few minutes. How could this happen?
On the same day that Estonia sank
it was rumored that the ferry was being used
to smuggle munitions.
It was dismissed
as pure conspiracy theories.
The load can be impossible
have had anything to do with the accident.
I already understood there and then
that if it was possible to
-that Estonia had been used to
smuggle secret military equipment
- probably Soviet equipment,
that would be an incredibly big deal.
For the tenth anniversary of the accident, I got
an email from Lennart Henriksson-
-who had been head of customs in Värtan.
Estonia and other ferries arrived.
He had something to tell.
A few weeks before the accident
he was called to his boss.
Together they had gone to the boss
for the customs region here in Stockholm.
The boss said:
"There will be some cars like you
shall be admitted without inspection. "
"Do not visit? Who said that?"
"It's an order," I received
in response. "From the highest place."
"As high as you can get."
"Is it from the king?"
"No, but it's very high up."
The first car arrived on September 14
- two weeks before the accident.
He got a call and they said:
"Now comes one of these cars."
He went down to the ferry terminal,
and the ferry came in.
He got to see which car did not
would check but looked in it anyway.
I said that the customs kept control. He
looked at me but asked no questions.
I said "I want to look a little in the car"
and opened some boxes.
As I understood it, it was
military electronics in the boxes.
On September 20, Henriksson said,
so this happened for the second time.
He was called. "There's one
another car to let you through. "
It was a larger car with a double
as large a load as the first
-but as he could see
so it was the same type of cargo.
He went on vacation, so when the accident
happened he was not in Stockholm.
So he does not know
if there was any cargo then, that night.
It had been rumored that it had been
military transport in Estonia.
But it had been unconfirmed.
Now I was sitting with a man in front of me-
-who could tell,
from his own experience-
-that it had happened,
and very close to the accident.
The weeks before the sinking of Estonia
just over ten years ago
-the ferry was used for secret shipping
of military equipment.
The speculations
proved to be true.
It is now confirmed that it has been shipped
military equipment on board Estonia.
The Armed Forces conducts operations
which is partly secret.
It's pretty natural
that we have such business.
This is part of such a
activity that I can not comment on.
We want to know what happened,
and we are as surprised as others
-of the news that steamed down the other day.
That's remarkable
and shocking.
Usually, transportation is bypassed
military equipment of rigorous rules.
But here the Armed Forces has used
of a civilian passenger ferry
-to carry military goods.
It is completely unacceptable to smuggle
munitions on a passenger ferry.
Civilians are then exposed
for an obvious danger.
It struck like a bomb in society.
The government appointed an inquiry for
to ascertain whether this had happened.
Always like us
from time to time, through the
-have heard this kind of statement,
always got them rejected.
That is why the government has decided
to summon Johan Hirschfeldt-
-give him the task of going through-
-all the month of September for
the accident year 1994 and thereby ascertain:
Has there been that type
of transports on board Estonia?
Mona Sahlin, who took care of
The Estonia issue, was very upset.
I interviewed her, and she showed
that this had shaken her.
That one had transported,
secretly, military equipment
-so close to the accident without the defense
had told something after the accident.
People had been sitting here
at customs and in the defense
-and knew things that were essential
for the investigation, for the relatives
-and did not say anything.
THE CURSE OF ESTONIA
The report raises questions
around the Estonian disaster
The interview with Lennart Henriksson
in Swedish television everything changed.
The rumors that had aroused
such a joke for ten years
-suddenly considered credible
and were no longer free fantasies.
WE HOPE FOR A NEW INVESTIGATION!
In 2005, the Estonian established
the government a Commission
-for the purpose of investigating the smuggling
of military equipment in Estonia.
I headed the Commission.
The Swedish authorities
first promised to cooperate with us.
But when we started going into details
concerning the covert operation
-they gave us conflicting information.
My conclusion was that the information
was not reliable.
We did not arrive
to especially much.
We did not manage to find out what it was
was the question of whether and where it came from.
It was largely due to
that the Swedish authorities
-not willing to cooperate.
It has been clarified that the Armed Forces
-at two occasions
during the month of September 1994-
-transported defense equipment
on M / S Estonia.
It took place on 14 and 20 September.
The equipment has passed
of electronic equipment
-no connection to weapon system-
and the equipment does not belong to anyone
part has been of an explosive nature.
Exactly what is classified, as well
from which country the equipment came.
Only the Minister of Defense
received that information today.
The information is scarce,
all with reference to confidentiality.
As for the night when Estonia sank
it is said that no
-which indicates that the Armed Forces
transported something.
I feel confident in that.
But you see how I am
has formulated me in the paper.
"They gave me no reason to assume
that they sought to transport equipment. "
What Hirschfeldt came to the conclusion was that
transports Henriksson told about
-the 14th and 20th of September
had taken place
-and it was the Swedish defense
who had stood for them.
He also showed that there was no indication
-that the defense had had
any transport on the night of the accident.
It was an incredible disappointment.
I felt that too.
It was like nothing came of it all.
The whole thing was swept under the carpet.
- despite what I had perceived
from Mona Sahlin:
That she was very interested
of going to the bottom with this.
Hirschfeldt has been known for
to have a good memory
and his investigation
was very short and limited.
When we had a hearing in the Riksdag
a few weeks later-
-so we asked the question
how the ordering had taken place.
Who ordered the customs officer
to let through the contraband?
Hirschfeldt said he had nothing
memory of it. He did not remember.
When we asked about the background material
which are not included in the report itself
- he said he had burned up
the background material.
-The background material is not preserved.
-Why not?
I chose not to report anything like that.
I chose to present the report.
For what reasons does not exist
the background material left?
I came to the conclusion that it was on it
the manner in which the mission was to be carried out.
As far as I know, it has never happened
in Swedish administrative history
-that a state investigation
destroys its background material.
There is nothing to perceive:
"Maybe you should destroy it!"
Someone has to explicitly say, "Everything
background material shall be destroyed. "
What was done
clearly showed that the Armed Forces
- had no interest in
to reach on this issue.
No private companies were investigated
been involved-
-or other countries
intelligence services.
They did not find out anything-
-so Hirschfeldt's investigation is correct,
but it is completely uninteresting.
It just confirmed
what the customs official had acknowledged
-but it did not find out anything else.
In the new Baltics
so prevailed the Wild West mood
-with weapons and all sorts of things-
-which was sold and bought
and was expelled from the land.
One who experienced this situation-
-was the Swedish military attaché on
that time in the Baltics:Sören Lindman.
There may have been goods in Russia
carried across the border into Estonia
-and shipped on to Sweden,
perhaps without the knowledge of the authorities.
He did not know the transports as
happened with Estonia shortly before the accident.
He concluded that it was not
the normal intelligence service
who had organized the transports.
It must have been organized
of the most secretive
-of the Swedish
military intelligence.
The regular intelligence service
activities he would have known.
But he did not.
It must have been KSI.
Special Collection Office:
Sweden's secret spy organization.
That explains the incredible
confidentiality of transport
-if KSI was involved.
Nothing was allowed to come out
reveal details about KSI's operations.
- Did you work with them?
-I know they were there.
But cooperation or not?
I leave that open.
Did you help them get equipment?
I do not answer that question.
-1994 we are talking about now. September 1994.
-Yes.
- Did you help them with equipment?
-I do not answer that question.
The Estonia accident is surrounded by such
a lot of secrecy and stamps.
It must, as I see it,
indicate that you are
-for what the truth should turn out to be.
What I can say with certainty
has happened during these 25 years-
-since the night of the sinking is that
authorities do not want to find out
-what was on board Estonias
cargo deck during the night of sinking.
The biggest question mark
touch the photos taken on October 2nd.
Four days after the sinking.
The pictures show that the railings
on the boarding ramp ...
They are sawn off
outside the ship on the seabed.
Here's something
which is very, very wrong.
I thought about it a lot
why the railings were outside the ship.
They show that someone has tried
get on the cargo deck. Why?
Just a defense force
can act so powerfully-
-and get in
on a ship's cargo deck.
The only thing that can motivate
such an action is if there are
-a state affairs or military
urgent cargo on board. Nothing else.
In these interpellation debates
which I took the initiative
- I hoped to be able to push forward answers
and pursue further investigation.
You should be able to trust
on its Armed Forces.
You should be able to trust your government.
That they do their utmost
in a situation like this.
If you can not do that, then something is
fundamental flaws in society.
Thank you, Madam President. It is
very clear images showing
-that someone has cut off
on-board ramp
-something of the next 24 hours
after the sinking.
This is actual evidence for
activities that we do not know
-and which has not happened
under the direction of the Accident Investigation Board.
Why has the Prime Minister not found
it is important to find the answer to:
What are these?
What kind of activities do they have
participated in, and what was the purpose?
Thanks. - Minister of Public Works.
The subtitle all the time
when Ångström expresses
- is that here is a minister
which would deliberately conceal truths.
It does not matter how many
times I look him in the eye-
-and says:"That's not me."
I do not know if
some other dives - point.
Absolutely no other dives. Against
in the light of what I have stated here-
- I do not think so
there are sufficient reasons
-to allow underwater-
operations at the wreck of M / S Estonia-
-and no reason either
to take measures in connection with
-of any activity
around the wreck of M / S Estonia.
The Prime Minister's response to the interpellation
about not doing anything-
-gives the impression, for many,
that the government participates in
-to obscure the circumstances
and the activities of the Armed Forces
-in connection with the sinking of Estonia,
and it does not feel good.
Even a non-answer can be an answer.
If you do not want to investigate
so maybe that says something too.
Everything indicates that the Swedish
The Armed Forces is aware of
-about the intrusion on the cargo deck between
on September 28 and October 2.
Why one can only speculate,
but it presupposes something-
-which is of great state
or military interest.
I'm convinced that the truth about
what was on Estonia's cargo deck
-is an issue as well
will get an answer.
The basis of my contacts within
various intelligence services are simple:
They know they can trust me.
Tomlinson told about the smuggling
aboard Estonia 1998-
-which was six years before the Swedish
the customs official's TV revealed.
I was sitting in a hotel room in Auckland
to make a different kind of story-
-when I suddenly got information
on a ferry sinking in the Baltic Sea
and a smuggling operation
which involved MI6.
I immediately decided
to get to the bottom of that story.
Further investigations
led me to a new source.
An MI6 agent on active duty gave me
information about what actually happened.
Russia had, on two occasions,
demanded that the countries of the
- would stop the smuggling.
The first requirement reached Estonia in 1993
via diplomatic channels.
They knew about the smuggling on the ferry
and ordered Estonia to stop.
Estonia ignored the demand.
The following year, just before the sinking,
Russia turned directly to MI6.
"We know about smuggling, and we know
that it takes place on board Estonia. "
"Stop this immediately. Otherwise ..."
While Swedes and Estonians
mourned their dead
-who followed the ferry to the bottom of the sea-
- there was panic behind
intelligence lantern doors.
Sweden has acknowledged the smuggling on board
in Estonia in the weeks before the accident.
However, my sources have confirmed that
smuggling took place during the night of the accident.
The contraband was critical information
on the Russian missile program
as well as electronic parts
linked to the missile program.
A high-ranking person
within the Swedish intelligence service
-must have said to the Prime Minister:
"You intend to salvage the ferry
to investigate the accident. "
"It absolutely must not happen."
Everything was very careless. Customs and
border guards barely existed.
You could carry what you wanted
wherever.
The investigation files I
came into contact with within the police
-confirmed that the public
version of the accident presented
- is by no means true.
When I got on board
I put my things away.
I put down my bag
and walked around a bit on the boat.
Then I understand
that the boat is delayed.
I'm looking at the clock,
and the boat is late by now.
Then I go out on deck and think
that I might have time to wave to Dad.
This is how I look over the parking lot.
There are barrier bands set up. I
think they were rebuilding.
One more explanation
why Estonia was delayed
-where there were two or three
trucks to the port
-which was alleged to come
from the Estonian Home Guard
-or people attached to the Home Guard.
There was a commotion.
The police did not want to let them on board.
The others, that is, the Home Guard,
which came with the cargo-
-did not give up.
I see that there will be a transport.
There are two or three motorcycles,
or four, which runs fairly fast.
They escort military vehicles
who rides on the boat.
I perceived it as it was
at least two, but there may have been more.
They were painted green
because they were military
-but it was also a car
with a rather large box on.
Or a flatbed with one like that
tarpaulin on, or something.
In short,
what was on board the trucks?
On the two, or three trucks,
there are different offers for the
- military technology was shipped.
Military electronics.
There was talk
on top-secret military technology
-which was brand new at the time.
Within the Russian military it is
much that is classified.
It's so secret
that if something is lost-
-or left
in foreign territories
- you do everything to destroy it
so it does not end up in the wrong hands.
When they're on, we go. You close
again, and then it's ready for departure.
I think, 'That's why we were
delayed. "The vehicles were waiting.
It's weird that it's military
vehicles on a passenger ship.
That which gets me
to think it's weird-
- was precisely this information
which emerged many years later.
That it was military transport
in Estonia, but not just that night.
But I saw that it was.
There must have been many who saw it.
There were others standing on deck.
The staff at the terminal and those who
worked on the boat must know about it.
I never thought of a journalist
from Sweden would find me-
-but they found me.
My name is Kadir Kaymaz.
When the accident occurred
I was Carl Övberg.
Estonia 1994 was ...
You could say chaos.
You could buy
all old Russian military stuff.
Even helicopters.
I sold cars to Estonia.
I went with the boat several times.
Maybe twenty.
But this evening
was a little different.
I went from the center of Tallinn to
the port by taxi. I was in a hurry.
But when we got to the port area
were the military there.
The military police stopped the taxi.
Taxi drivers
dropped me off outside the harbor.
I ran to the boat.
I was the last passenger.
When I looked down in front of the boat
I saw some military cars.
Military activity.
Almost ten, fifteen soldiers.
And military vehicles
with chapel and such red candles.
That's when I thought:
Maybe something's going on.
I have no evidence,
but I think they smuggled weapons
-or
any technical military equipment ...
... from the former Soviet Union.
When I came back to Stockholm
called my phone
-and there was a guy who said:
"Do not come to Estonia."
It was threatening,
so I stopped going to Estonia.
Maybe they did not like
my observations.
There are still many questions
which are unanswered around Estonia.
Why not confirm the authorities
military transport in Estonia?
I was a witness
to this event.
If Estonia had military cargo, it has
had consequences for the investigation.
That explains why
they wanted to cast the ship in concrete.
You did not enter the cargo deck
and controlled the load.
The ship's was not inspected
hull. Whether it had been damaged.
As you continue
to prevent further investigation
- we will not come
with one hundred percent security
-to be able to determine
the cause of the sinking.
It's just by going down and
inspect the appearance of the shipwreck
-as one can reach clarity,
and the government does not agree.
About the management of Estonia
shall meet the requirements
-how a state governed by the rule of law
such a huge accident
- so the authorities must do
the measures proposed
-to examine the ferry
where it is located
-and see what answers you can find, there
down, on what caused the accident.
To send divers down again to
examine the ferry more closely would be good.
With today's technology
maybe we can get answers.
It takes new dives to find
the truth. The sooner, the better.
The Finnish Maritime Administration
announced that they
-that the peace of the tomb over Estonia
out in the Baltic Sea has been broken.
You also suspect
that a diving robot has been sent down.
The truth about what happened
with Estonia is hidden in the Baltic Sea.
A diving expedition is required
to find out what happened.
The diving robot
has visual contact with the wreck.
-What the hell?
-Oh, fucking. Oh, fucking!