I'm thinking about how lucky I was
who managed to get me out of there.
Everything feels so much more authentic
and you value everything much more
-when you have almost lost your life.
I still do not understand why
the ship was not properly inspected.
Think about how slowly the Titanic sank
-and how fast Estonia sank.
I want an answer. What was that
what happened, and why did it happen?
I get no peace
until I get an answer.
My wish as a survivor is
that we are getting closer to the truth.
And I think
that the truth is something else-
-than what has
served the people so far.
I do not believe it was just
a bow visor that broke.
If that is the explanation one would
do not want to cover the ship with
and one would not ban
the filming of the ship.
Here we have a ferry that has sunk.
To date, it has not been investigated
if the hull was complete when she sank.
How could the ship sink?
-without a hole that let out air
from the bottom of the ship?
The ship did not sink for no reason.
There must be a hole.
It's so easy
to just go down and check.
You do not know
if it really was an accident.
In fact, it can
be something else that happened out there.
If you want to move on, you have to
make new dives down to Estonia's wreck.
We started from Rostock and set course
north, towards the wreck site.
The trip takes a little over two days.
Today is D-Day, and I think
that everyone has been looking forward to this.
Now it's finally time.
We will be in place
around five o'clock this afternoon.
The area around the sinking site, and
even the wreck, is protected by the peace of the grave.
This makes diving on the wreck difficult.
Previous expeditions
have encountered major problems.
What are your intentions? Come on.
My name is Jakob Olszewski.
I was a diver during the previous two
expeditions to the Estonian wreck.
This time
I am a diving consultant.
The boat is German flagged and Germany has
not written under the Tomb Peace Act.
This is international waters,
but we do not know what will happen.
Oh!
It looks like
there is a military ship
-just above our goal.
Above the wreck of Estonia.
They're waiting for us.
They were also present
at the two previous expeditions-
-so I expect no problems.
But you can never be completely sure.
When we can read the text
on the ship side-
-so we see that it is the Finnish coast-
the guard's largest ship Turva.
Turva has placed itself on top of the wreck.
If they do not move
then we can not dive.
Turva, Turva,
this is M / S Fritz Reuter.
Fritz Reuter, Turva who answers.
I have a question:
Are you going to stay in your position,
or can you move?
I see that you are approaching spring
position. What are your intentions?
We are a documentary team
-who makes a documentary
about the Estonian disaster.
I understand. Do you intend to
engage in underwater activities?
Yes.
In that case, I must inform you of the
-that the wreck is considered a burial site
for all who died in the accident.
We are aware of that,
but we sail under the German flag.
That is why I think we should
be able to carry out our assignment.
A last question:
Has nine people of Finnish, Swedish
or Estonian nationality on board?
We have two Swedes on board.
Turva, this is Fritz Reuter.
Did you understand
that we are a German-flagged ship
-which is on international waters?
Turve here.
Yes, it is understood.
And with regard to maritime safety
are we prepared to move-
- half a mile away
from this position.
So good. Thanks so much.
Wow! This is great!
I did say
that the pimples are really nice.
Thank you, Finland!
When Turva chooses to move
we feel a great relief.
But they remained in place
and observed us all the time.
In order to have a reference on the sea surface
-then you have to throw out a shot line,
or a dive line.
It is incredibly important that the diving line
hits as close to the wreck as possible.
We have to move the dive line.
Launch the ROV, please.
ROV launched.
Thanks.
Okay, drive towards the dive line.
Turn the ROV 90 degrees to the left.
90 degrees to the left, please.
We have not yet
visual contact with the diving line.
-Okay, now I see it.
-We have visual contact with the diving line.
-I'm starting to dive.
-Thank you, we're starting to dive.
We are now five meters below the water surface.
Celebrate more diving line.
The diving line is amidships,
25 meters away.
The Finnish Maritime Administration announces
in a press release
-that they believe the peace of the grave over the wreck
Estonia out in the Baltic Sea has been broken.
You also suspect
that a diving robot has been sent down
- despite calls not to do so,
and despite the fact that there is grave peace.
We have Petteri Partanen with us
from the Finnish Maritime Administration.
-Has anyone been arrested?
-No.
We have no legal powers
in international waters.
- Are you monitoring the ship?
-Yes, uninterrupted.
I hope it is a good sight
down there. We're going down to 70 meters.
60 meters.
We should start approaching.
Pretty much jellyfish.
We are now down to a depth of 67 meters.
Okay, when we get down we get
hope it's ... Well, there.
The ROV has visual contact
with the wreck.
The diving line is perfectly placed
between us and Turva. It looks good.
It is located directly between the bow thrusters.
The diving line is located between the bow thrusters.
We'll get out on the bulb here.
Around 73 meters deep on the bulb.
The ROV has visual contact
with Estonia's bulb.
The bow looks nice.
Celebrate more diving line
calm and careful, thank you.
Celebrate more diving line.
We follow the fender on the port side-
-in western direction.
Roger.
-What's that?
-Wait. Now we'll see here ...
This must be the hole
as the Rockwater divers did in 1994.
In December 1994, they made two holes,
so we should find another one over here.
Yes, and here's the second hole.
I now have good documentation
of the two Rockwater holes.
Roger.
Rockwater would cover the holes
when finished, but it is open.
But it may have been done later.
-Now I'm driving back.
-ROB returns to the dive line.
It seems to have tipped over a lot.
It is at quite an angle.
The ship appears to have
quite strong tilt-
- towards starboard side.
I would guess at about 130 degrees.
Is Turva still in position?
Can you go starboard out?
I go out and walk around the line again,
and then we go down and go aft.
Celebrate more dive line, please.
Celebrate more diving line.
-This must be the fender.
-Is it starboard fender?
The ROV is located
at Estonia's starboard fender.
We follow it aft.
-Fire down.
-Provides more diving line.
There are rumors of a hole that explains
why the boat sinks so fast.
We do not know if it has been filmed before.
This is the first review of
possible damage to that part of the boat.
-You can see quite well.
-Yes, now we are at 85 meters deep.
There is quite a lot of color left. She
is completely white above the blue fender.
This looks like mud.
It's Baltic clay.
-Here we have ... Yes, that's rock.
-The line is now 40 meters from the stern.
Yes, this
must be the filling stone.
It's just there, as well.
But if you follow the fender further now
then we have it as a reference.
Wait.
Now we'll see here ...
-Are you already in ...?
-There, turn there.
Where the hell are we now?
The boat ends here.
Oops, look!
That looks like a ... No.
I'll see if I can get a better one
Angle. I was a little surprised.
Is it the fender?
Can you try to come
so you see ...? Can you see in?
Oh, fucking!
It is completely imprinted here.
-Now I look straight into the boat.
-It is therefore completely inflated.
Yes, up on the starboard side
is it fully depressed, like one meter.
The fender is completely mashed.
-Oh oh oh!
-Yes, it's a ...
I'll see if I can
can get a little down to the side.
I'm coming across the sandbank behind,
so I have to get up and go over a bit.
There we are above the fender. It is
something around there, like an o or an s.
There you see it. It really looks
looks like something's written there.
An s or an o.
Something with a round bottom edge.
Estonia was not on the sidelines.
No, it said Estline,
so it can be the bottom of a s.
There's a towel. I do not know
if we are at the "swimming pool area".
I think we're further behind.
If we are at the s on Estline
are we further back.
-But how could they have missed that?
-They can not if they have dived here.
-The diving line is amidships.
-ROB is a midshipman in Estonia.
We have made an interesting discovery
and stops at this position.
Roger.
-There the fender is fully pressed.
-The dive line is directly above the wreck.
But is this from ...?
Is it from the sinking itself?
-She kind of got out of the water.
-I'm checking again.
I've seen a lot of wrecks.
It seems to be
really a lot of power in this one.
-Here it is ...
-It is steel beams that have fallen off.
The hull is completely blown out here, of course.
It points out a large piece of metal here.
This is a very clear,
and very large, damage.
It's hard to get a better angle.
It feels a little insecure.
Things stand out here, but I do
try to get as close as possible.
But look at this, then!
-It's a hole.
-Any big.
It does not look like
as it has only been a "tension".
It is completely pressed.
Which side did she lean on
when she sank?
She leans towards starboard.
-It's starboard side we're looking at.
-Yes, and I mean, it's like ...
Would it be a hole somewhere
in the boat it would be here.
-It's long too. Really long.
-Oh oh oh!
- Are you having an abortion now?
-Yes, we go to the surface.
Celebrate the dive line.
We take the ROV to the surface.
We get to watch the 4K video as well,
but it was an injury we saw there.
-The fender was completely off.
-Yes Yes.
At first I thought we were there
the stern, because the boat just ran out.
-Covers the diving line.
-I take it slow.
Fucking!
A little after twelve, then it slams,
two very powerful bangs.
It sounds like we're going through ice.
Pretty soon after that, the ship does
a maneuver violently to starboard.
It was as if the ship
was hit by something.
Then all the glass in the cafeteria was smashed
behind me. It did not feel good.
Are you coming to the rescue?
It looks very bad here now!
I am very pleased that we,
after a few days-
-really can say that we have done
a groundbreaking find.
We have found damage.
Very large damage.
This can not be dismissed as
speculations. The damage is there.
A German-flagged ship is suspected of having
disturbed the peace of the grave around M / S Estonia.
The Finnish Maritime Administration
believe that the purpose was to photograph the wreck.
-You take the incident seriously.
-Such things like this should not happen.
You should not dive with anyone
appliances, without leaving the area alone.
Finnish Maritime Surveillance
have had contact with the ship.
There are Swedish citizens on board,
but you do not know who they are.
Once we have documented the damage
there were helicopters and planes.
We ended the operation.
What happens now?
We cooperate with Finnish
and international authorities.
We observe the ship's activities
very carefully.
Two Swedes are accused of having
desecrated Estonia's grave
On Saturday, it is 25 years since Estonia
fell. 852 people died in the accident.
Twenty-five years ago, I survived
M / S Estonia's sinking.
I got to come home to my family
and live on.
Thousands of other people watched
not parts of his family again.
It was a tough night, but it
was also difficult to live on.
To be a survivor. A witness.
I could not stand the
-how we survivors and relatives
were not listened to.
That our testimonies were not counted
and relatives were not allowed to join
and make important decisions.
How could a country like Sweden
act that way?
To me, it was incomprehensible.
Unfortunately
the handling still affects us.
The decisions that were made
or not understood
-is like rings on the water
and reproduces indefinitely.
Today my thoughts go to all of you
who lost your loved ones that night
-other survivors-
-and to all my fellow passengers
who never got to come home again.
Several of those who spoke
at the memorial service
brought the claim
on a new, independent investigation.
Look at all the facts on the table.
Come to the logical conclusion-
-to appoint an independent
international inquiry.
Let's escape
all conspiracy theories.
The Ministry of Justice declared,
the same evening, in a press release
-that the government opposed
a new, independent inquiry.
Same day night.
We're on our way to Linus Andersson,
who was out on the Baltic Sea.
He is trained in ship technology
-and one of the Nordic countries
leading experts on wreck damage.
He has analyzed the material
from Estonia.
We will see for the first time
what he has found.
In the pictures and films I have-
managed to get the position out of the injury
on the wreck and the size of the damage.
As we can see from this 3D model
then we have the damage at this point.
It is definitely no small injury.
Can you explain
how we drove on the Baltic Sea?
When we arrived
we put down the diving line.
The diving line ends up perfectly
here at the bow, between the trustees.
Then we went up along the hull
to the fender.
So we have some kind of reference point.
The ROV drives on
about a third of the stern
-where we saw this injury.
Something I have noticed when I have
checked various drawings are-
-that the Estline text
have been to different places.
I have not used the text,
but of rows of windows and windows.
These are fixed points
where they should be on the drawings.
In this model we only see
the opening in the hull itself.
Where it is open into the boat.
How far is it from here to there?
It can continue longer,
but the minimum measurement is four meters.
Four meters in reality. If we
see how high it is in the ceiling here ...
-It is 2.5 m to the roof in here.
-So the damage continues for another 1.5 m.
-Fuck, it's big.
-Really big.
And 1.5 meters at the widest point.
The distance from the outside of the curtain
and here corresponds to the width of the damage.
And 1.5 meters higher than the ceiling.
Really big.
-Where is the damage we have observed?
-The damage is here.
Over here. So it's ...
Here we have a shot. Do you see?
To an untrained eye, it looks like
it is where people lie and sleep.
In the middle of the night
it's full of people in the cabins.
It's in the middle of the passengers.
This feels
as an impact injury to me.
As it is printed here ...
A force has really mashed the
-and made it fold twice.
And as it looks there ...
So. It's almost exactly that fender
lies here - weight over himself.
The question is
how and when it has arisen.
The Meyer shipyard that built Estonia
claims that there were
-more explosive charges on board
which detonated during the disaster.
Someone placed,
according to the yard's experts
explosives on board Estonia,
which detonated as the boat sank.
According to the report, it is likely
-that the damage in certain areas
has been caused by explosions.
German experts discovered that two, three
explosions caused holes in the hull.
There was a loud bang, and so on
another, whereupon the ship heeled.
This indicates explosions.
-Henrik.
-Frank.
My name is Frank Børresen
and is the war captain.
I work as a staff officer
for diving operations.
I have seen
a large number of explosions
-and how they affect
motor vehicles and ships.
I'm an expert on clearing
of explosive objects, diving
-as well as marine mine action.
Yes, there I see the damage begins.
What is characteristic here
is that it is very elongated.
-Can you see the distances here?
-Yes, it's four meters up there.
The graphics clearly show
that the ship's side has been pressed in.
If one compares with known explosions-
-on the USS Cole or the tankers
in the Persian Gulf this year
-you see that the metal is always bent
inward by explosions from outside.
Outward if the explosion occurs from within.
As if something hits a hole in the hull.
I can not rule out an explosion-
-but I think it works
very unlikely that this is the case.
In that case, the metal would go a long way
to a greater extent have been bent inwards.
I do not see that peeling either
of color caused by explosions.
The metal is not bent enough
for it to be an explosion.
Based on the pictures and graphics
it appears as if
-that an external force
has been pressed into the hull side.
It's in the middle of ... The damage is
located right on the waterline.
Which indicates?
Given the location, the ship can
have been hit by another object.
But I do not have enough skills
to comment further on.
My name is Jørgen Amdahl and I am
Professor of Marine Engineering at NTNU.
My work largely consists of
analyzes of the consequences of
collisions between ships, and
between ships and oil platforms.
It's a pretty extensive injury.
It looks like
the color has been blown off
-which may indicate a collision
with one or another object.
An external influence.
The questions you are happy to ask yourself are:
How could this have happened?
And what is the reason?
There are many possible explanations
to how this may have happened.
The ship may have hit something
which floated in the water.
It could be the bow visor.
There should be damage to the bow visor
if that was what hit the page.
Yes, there is significant damage
on the book visor.
Let's see...
It's probably the bulb
who caused that.
On this page I do not see
particularly large scratch marks.
I see no marks indicating
that the bow visor caused the damage.
That's weird. That's likely
that they collided with the bow visor.
Could it have been something else
on the sea surface?
The damage is so great
that one cannot exclude
-that it has had an impact
on the sinking process.
One can calculate, with quite large
accuracy, the force required
-to cause such damage.
You can also calculate which mass
the object that hit the ship had.
So this
should probably be investigated further.
Every autumn, at this time,
I feel an anxiety in my body.
I have been doing this every year since 1994.
Afterwards, I was told by eyewitnesses-
-that Hjørund was together
with his mother when the boat sank.
It was such a steep staircase
that Hjørund did not have the strength to climb up.
His mother
chose not to leave him.
She was not strong enough to get
with him Hjørund up the stairs.
I have been subjected to two abuses.
One is that the ferry sank
and I lost my son.
The second is that the Swedes decided
that the ferry would be left where it was.
There must be another reason
that they have not salvaged it.
Why is this still important today?
Because we do not know
how the accident happened.
For me, this is about the future
maritime safety for my descendants
-and in different parts of the world.
In such a great catastrophe,
as Estonia is
- you have to know what happened
and why it happened
-and above all
that it will not happen again.
And I'm convinced
that the truth will come to an end.
-I'm excited about what you've found.
-Yes I understand that.
Then we'll see ... What we have done-
-is that we have built up
an element model of the ship
-of a certain length.
Then we drove in an object
on the ship side
-to see what forces
and energies required
-to cause the damage
as you have observed with the ROV.
We see that the ship's side is pressed in.
We also get a crime
on the side plates of the vessel.
And an extensive deformation
of the frame and the half frame.
Here we have removed the bullet to get
a better insight into the course of the damage.
It is very obvious
how similar your animation is to reality.
The area of ​​damage is very similar
which has been observed with the camera.
We discovered that the maximum power
we get here is about 500-600 tons.
It is the force required to
that kind of damage should occur.
-God, it's a huge force.
-Yes, it's a pretty big force.
What does this really mean?
It can correspond
an object weighing one thousand tonnes
and moves at four knots.
A big fishing boat, maybe.
It can also be an object
weighing five thousand tonnes
-which moves at 1.9 knots.
It corresponds to
a medium-sized supply vessel.
This is a floating object
in the water there is no small object.
Even if it weighs a thousand tons
it is a large object.
It's absolutely incredible.
We last talked about the bow visor
may have hit the ship side.
The bow visor weighs 55 tons.
55 tons is a very small mass
in this context. It is.
If we are talking about a thousand tons
it would correspond to twenty bow visors.
The bow visor has not caused the damage.
I probably dare say so much.
So yes.
Shall we open the door?
I'm a little "shaken".
We talked about me
would ask you a lot of stuff-
-but I actually did
a little "sat out" of this.
I was a little surprised myself
while I was working on this.
You have not taken in so you crack?
No, we care about being objective.
We really are.
It is also possible to a stone
on the seabed, the vessel
-which may increase the power.
But that presupposes that it exists
stone there that supports the seabed.
But that possibility exists.
A bottom investigation was done when
one would "cover" with concrete.
There it is established that it is
a deep segment with loose clay
-which is then followed by
slightly harder moraine clay.
You go, of course
very deep down.
There is no indication that there are stones there.
It is not described
in the documentation, in any case.
No.
We've talked to first-hand sources,
especially those who survived the accident.
They have made exciting observations.
Here we have Carl Eric Reintamm,
who are survivors.
He is also up very early
walking deck. We can see a little.
When I get out of the ship
I do not see any people.
Where I am, there are no people.
I was one of the first to get there.
When I stand there, I look
of course out to sea, and down.
And then I see
something strange in the water.
I see something white that is
several times several meters large.
This is moving to the left
-and at the same time
then there are waves over this.
I've never done military service
and I have no idea
-how submarines look in the water.
It was dark in the water.
I have no idea-
-about a submarine
may look brighter than water.
But obviously
drove the ship on something.
What else can explain
that you hear sound
-which sounds
that the ship is driving through ice
-when you are down there where you are
hear everything that hits the ship?
Yes, of course it makes an impression.
And there are certain things
which can make one think a little extra.
Especially considering the
observations made at the bottom.
Does what he says sound reasonable?
I can not say
that it does not. He sees something.
And it is clear that it is ...
It is not certain that he sees everything.
A submarine is quite long, but he
must not have seen the whole submarine.
Submarines can weigh less than a thousand tons,
or several thousand tons.
We can see
if we can find some pictures.
"Kobben, submarine."
Does it say how big it is?
It's a pretty small boat.
We'll see if I can find more
information about the submarine's displacement.
Submarine failure ... In the Ula class, maybe?
A thousand tons.
Submarines like this
weighs about a thousand tons.
You can not pull any completely safe
conclusions based on this.
But anyhow
all testimonies should be evaluated.
This testimony
has never been valued.
It's an observation
which should be taken seriously. It is.
It's a mystery
how the ship was damaged.
If it happened before the ship sank
it's an even bigger mystery.
Based on the findings we have made,
what do you think should be done now?
Based on a technical and professional
estimate of the damage
- I think you should investigate
what may have caused the damage
-and if it may have contributed to
the course of events and its outcome.
This is new evidence
which no one has reported before.
Therefore, one must try to find
an explanation. I think so.
Accidents are usually followed by
different theories and explanations
-who depend on
different people's knowledge
-and, perhaps, the purposes.
Estonia is associated with
the many theories that have emerged
-but you have to be
open to discussing everything.
It is, in any case,
wrong to sweep things under the carpet
-because you fear the debate.
Welcome.
We have a fairly short presentation-
-where we want to inform about some
findings concerning the Estonian disaster.
During our work we have realized that
there are more question marks than answers
-about what happened to Estonia
on September 28, 1994.
You will see an ROV recording
of starboard side of Estonia.
It will set
The Estonia disaster in a new light.
If you follow the fender further now
then we have it as a reference.
Wait.
The boat ends here.
Oops, look!
That looks like a ... No.
That's too damn good!
Heads must roll here, then.
You can not talk this out.
It's an incredible injury.
This is a real scandal
which does not resemble anything.
I'm not just upset
- I'm pissed.
That's dramatic.
Especially that it was not discovered
when the accident report was written.
Shocking, actually.
It's something
which I have been waiting for all these years.
It seems to be revolutionary.
Now you have to admit tamejtusan
and tell me what really happened.
That knowledge exists,
and we want to know it!
A new investigation
is not really necessary.
But it is necessary
that one speaks the truth and tells:
"This is what happened."
This is a must
taken up as far as possible.
Whatever the consequences.
It is hard to say
what caused the hole-
-because it is something that has
hit the ship from the outside.
We did not know this before,
so it's a brand new find.
Why it has not been discovered
previously I can not answer.
All authorities should take a look.
Absolutely also Estonian authorities.
I'm looking at this
as a groundbreaking find.
After this, I think
-that it is impossible
for the Estonian authorities
-not to act.
-It's completely imprinted here.
-Yes, now I'm looking straight into the boat.
That was it. What do you think about it?
I think I need time
to melt the shaking images.
I feel insecure because
I'm not a maritime expert.
I'm not sure what I am
have seen and how I should interpret it.
The main problem is of course that
three countries have agreed
-that it should neither be allowed
to dive at or to film the wreck.
But can it be so
that the agreement in question
-when it comes to finding out
what happened to estonia?
We lack authority
to comment on that matter.
This is completely new information
which we must have time to digest.
We will pass this on
the information to our experts.
Then we'll see
what the next step will be.
Losing a loved one
in a disaster like this is difficult.
It takes time to get over.
That late, almost twenty-six years later-
- find out that it probably is
there has been a huge blackout-
-and that everything you have done that has
been so strange in the Estonia question-
-because you wanted to hide
the cause of the sinking ...
The conspiracy theories circulating
I have only devoted fleeting thoughts.
But when you look
such a large hole in the ship's side
-which no one has investigated
or followed up
-that's what you think
that it can be a turning point.
I feel a little that it has
been worth the wait so long.
That there is more hope now,
to find out.
I would like to
arrive at the truth now.
For us who have worked for many years
with this issue in different ways
-so this is not the end point,
but this is a starting point.
It is a starting point for the next phase
in the case of Estonia.